<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certein letters vvherin is set forth a discourse of the peace that was attempted and sought to haue bin put in effecte by the lords and states of Holland and Zelande in the yeare of oure Lorde 1574 Also a supplication put vp by the saide States of Hollande and Zeland, and other places of the Low Countryes to the king: together with the aunsvvere and a reply vppon the same, and diuers other particularities.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101103</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836927</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1223)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 965:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certein letters vvherin is set forth a discourse of the peace that was attempted and sought to haue bin put in effecte by the lords and states of Holland and Zelande in the yeare of oure Lorde 1574 Also a supplication put vp by the saide States of Hollande and Zeland, and other places of the Low Countryes to the king: together with the aunsvvere and a reply vppon the same, and diuers other particularities.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fleetestreate by Thomas Marshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Translated from J. Perrenot and others."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; pages torn, marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:1"/>
            <p>CERTEIN LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERS VVHERIN IS SET forth a Diſcourſe of the Peace that was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted and ſought to haue bin put in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte by the Lords and States of Holland and Zelande in the yeare of oure Lorde 1574.</p>
            <p>ALSO A SVPPLICATION put vp by the ſaid States of Hollande and Zeland, and other places of the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes to the King: together with the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere and a Reply vppon the ſame, and diuers other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord God take me not away with the wicked, nor with them that commit iniquitie, which ſpeake peace to their neighbours, &amp; imagine miſchiefe in their harts.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Fleeteſtreate by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Marſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO</hi> 1576.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the intent to giue ſome lighte to ſuche as are not acquainted with the ſtate of the affayres and controuerſies of Hollande and Zelande, and to ſtoppe the mouthes of malicious aduerſaries, which ceaſſe not to reporte al maner of vntruth and reproch of the noble valeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and vertuous prince the Prince of Orendge &amp; his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; of the iuſt caſe which they maintein: here is tranſlated a ſhort Diſcourſe, of the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnial cauſe and ground of their entering into Armes, togither with a nomber of weyghtie &amp; ſubſtantial reaſons, wherby they iuſtifie their doing by good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and equitie. And it is the rather ſet forthe at this tyme, becauſe ſome of the parties and authors therof bee now here, as <hi>Mounſieur Sainct Aldegond,</hi> and <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Champagny</hi> and others, who may iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify the ſame (as neede ſhall requyre) to the open mainfeſtation of the truth with out further trauel. Read with aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and iudge indifferently, as the righte of the matter ſhall leade the.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <hi>Sum Dea, quae rara, &amp; paucis, Occaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nota.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_epistle">
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:3"/>
            <head>To his very friend E. B. eſquier affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate friend and deuotiſte ſeruaunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fayre and vertuous Lady the Counteſſe of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenberghe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His olde prouerbe (as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly all other) hath his grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> experience, <hi>Malus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, malamens,</hi> an euill affection maketh an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill construction. Men wrest or driue the interpretacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of doings to the frame of their owne coceits, which they deriue from the fauour or disfauour that they haue ſettled in their owne perſwaſions. It is not vnknowen what extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſcourſes, &amp; what priuate fanſies in common meeti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, are daily made of the caſe of our neighbours in the low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Such maner of debatinge where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue diſtracted you ſeeme to be the cauſe of your question, wherof you deſire to be reſolued in your letters.
<pb facs="tcp:1223:4"/>You coulde not haue written to a man more indifferent than I am: who am as farre from parcialitie, as he that loueth, (that is to ſay preferreth) neither party before other, but our country before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both. I do therefore (as I wish you to doe) ſet the pin of the beame eauen, and examine the weight of either ſkale. Let vs then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the ſides, and begin with the sharper, that we maye haue the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ending.</p>
            <p>First I will call to minde, what thone of thoſe ſides obiecteth:</p>
            <p>Secondly what thother aunſwereth: And thirdly what to drawe to concerne our ſelues.</p>
            <p>In the matter of obiection, let vs ſee what ſtrength it hath in iustice:</p>
            <p>In the matter of defence, let vs ſee what weight it hath in equitie:</p>
            <p>And for the matter of Our ſelues, let vs ſee what neceſſity, what commodity, what right, and what facilitie it is ſaid to beare, to draw vs to any ſide.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:4"/>
            <p>It is ſayd by ſome, which are loth that Spaine should be weaker or Englande ſtronger, that the Prince of Orendge &amp; his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are rebels in Armes agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt their natural Prince, and maintayners of a most daungerous preſident againſt all Princes.</p>
            <p>To this is aunſwered on thother part (as in this booke you shal ſee diſcourſed) that there is difference of the bande &amp; maner of their ſubiection from other. None of them holdeth that a king maye be shaken of by his ſubiects: but they all ſaye, that Lords electible vpon pacts &amp; conditions are alſo reiectible accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the ſame pacts &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Dominions ſubiecte to the ciuill lawes, which are not the Lawes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. The order of eche ſtate is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: not all States haue kings. Some haue other formes of gouernment. Not all kingdoms haue like maner of admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or receyuings of kings. Som follow natural ſucceſsion of bloud: ſome Choiſe:
<pb facs="tcp:1223:5"/>ſome Lot or chaunce. Some kings or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers haue ſimple &amp; abſolute power: ſome limitted &amp; circumſcribed. Therles of Holland and Zealand (as is well knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; many examples haue proued, at their <hi>Ioyous entree</hi> that is to ſaye, at ther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuinge to inauguration or ſeiſen of their Eſtate) be bound by oth to preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed pacts &amp; orders: whereby not onelye their forme of rule is bounded, but alſo vpon diuers points the ſubiects homage &amp; allegiance expreſly diſcharged. And that diſcharg in fact hath bin executed, &amp; by ſuch fact, (ſay they,) the aunceſters of the Prince himſelf that now chargeth them, haue bin receyued. The Prince and ſtates of that Country alledge the othe of their Earle, the preciſe forme of aſſoylme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon his breach of their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges: they produce one chiefe point, that they ought not to be pestered with gouernaunce or garriſon of ſtraungers: they recken vp thintollerable, outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; manifest oppreſsions done vpon
<pb facs="tcp:1223:5"/>them, and the euident practiſe to bring that free Nation to most vnſufferable ſeruitude: they shield themſelues vnder the liberty &amp; right of Nature, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of agreements, the othes of their Princes, their power of refuſall vppon their Princes periurie, wyth many like matters, whereof they make the worlde Iudges by their many Proteſtacions, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologies, Iustifications, &amp; Supplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to the ſtates of thempyre, &amp; other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: alwayes ſeuering their caſe from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubiectes of Naturall and abſolute Kinges.</p>
            <p>FOR (ſay they) in their caſe of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge the Kinge, theſe things are to be conſidered: the nature of the Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſubiection, &amp; the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistance, and thirdly the maner of the reſistance. The nature of the Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; the ſubiection ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in theſe two conſiderations. VVhether it hee <hi>Merum Imperium,</hi> that all thinges may be done <hi>Pro voluntate Regnanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> or it be <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratum,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1223:6"/>which is <hi>Temperatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Legibus,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Ruler hath his rule preſcribed him which way to rule, &amp; the Subiect a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne deſcribed him which way to obey. If the Gouernment be <hi>Merum &amp; abſolutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> then is the Perſon inferiour, a ſlaue and no ſubiecte. For in all due ſubiection there is <hi>Taxis,</hi> which is neuer in <hi>Voluntate.</hi> If the Gouernmente be <hi>Temperatum,</hi> then is thinferiour a ſubiect and no ſlaue.</p>
            <p>IN all ſubiection there is an honeſt liberty giuen by Law it ſelf, whereby all Actions and Pleas in Lawe are as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the ſubiect as to the ruler, for the maintenaunce of truth and equitie. In ſlauerie there is none ſuch: becauſe he is not to be meaſured but by the will of the Ruler, which howſoeuer it turneth, is his right: &amp; he hath no actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Appeal or Plea to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Then it followeth that the Law is the rightest Auctoritie, and the ſame is to be maintayned by all the iuſt and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full executers of it: for if the Lawe
<pb facs="tcp:1223:6"/>be not maynteined, the life of the whole common wealth is lost.</p>
            <p>This mayntenaunce of the Lawe no man doubteth vvhether it ought to bee or no: for it is thende vvhy Counſellers &amp; vnder magiſtrats are appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted: yea it is the cauſe of placing the higheſt Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate hymſelfe. So that to maintayne the Lavv, is iudged meete by all men: if the Lavv be iust.</p>
            <p>But whether the Law may be mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned agaynſt the Higheſt Magiſtrate or no, that is the doubt. For here upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this maintenance of Law is called reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and is called Rebellion?</p>
            <p>This question doth imply a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for it importeth that thone is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thother, &amp; no man can ſerue two Maisters: &amp; ſo ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the vvhole caſe in the righteouſnes of the Lavv, which for the preſent purpoſe is preſumed to be most iust &amp; most holy. VVhy then? The Perſon that is agaynst this Lavv, goeth aboute to diſanull that that is
<pb facs="tcp:1223:7"/>most iuſt and moſt holy, &amp; laboureth to bring in that, that is moſt vniust, most vnholy. For touchinge his owne perſon the queſtion and debate ſtandeth not, but for thinforcing of the ſubiects to the ſame.</p>
            <p>VVHY then, there is no doubt but as it is confeſſed of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knew God, and of them that do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe God, that iuſtice is to be maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt iniuſtice, Godlines against vngodlines, &amp; God against the deuill: els were the law no law, neither the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect a ſubiect: being (as I ſayd before) a perſon licenced to liue in liberty of law.</p>
            <p>Thus by the nature of Gouernment &amp; the ſubiection, it is euidente that the righteſt Magiſtrate may be reſiſted, &amp; this reſiſtance is truly a maintenaunce of Law &amp; equitie and ſo to be termed, and vntruly and vniustly called Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. For theſe words of rebellion and ſuche like cannot iustlye bee vſed, but where the wyll of the Ruler and the law
<pb facs="tcp:1223:7"/>are concurrent and agree in one.</p>
            <p>By this that hath bin ſaide of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment it ſelfe, enſueth a right aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the cauſe of reſista<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Nothing may cauſe reſistance to the Magistrate but the maintenaunce of righte and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: for there is no equitie in this, that the will of the ſubiect should ſtand for a lawe to the Prince, where the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect thinketh it vnmeete that the wil of his Prince should ſtande for a law of his ſubiection. This is againſt Iustice di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributiue, which the Heathen teach in their common wealth, &amp; flatly against the rule of GOD: <hi>Thou ſhalte not do to thy Neighbour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou vvilt not haue don to thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SO then he that hath law &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the law, is reſiſted on which part ſoeuer he be: &amp; he that reſisteth the law is a rebell and traitour whoſoeuer he be: for the law is <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> life of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale. And the conſideration of reſiſtance ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in the perſon, vnleſſe hee haue the law with him: if he be not <hi>Lex loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1223:8"/>he is not reſisted, but reſisteth.</p>
            <p>But euery man may not reſist. They onely that are made keepers of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth: otherwyſe there would be a confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and euery man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croche vpon an others office. The shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloude is murther in euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man: but if a Magistrate do it, he doth it lawfully, and is excuſed before man, and doth his dutie to God: For hee beareth not the ſword in vaine.</p>
            <p>IN ſum, where the kind of Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is tempered by Law, &amp; the Prince hath aſwell to liue by law as the ſubiect: if the Prince wil breake this Law which is iust, &amp; enforce an obedience to a law vniuſt against the will of the Subiects: the law may be maintayned agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt him, by ſuch as are appointed from God &amp; the law, to be Gardians &amp; kepers of the law. But the caſe of the Prince of Orenge &amp; his aſsociats ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> ſame termes. The king with whom he hath to deale had auctoritie <hi>Temperatam Laegibus:</hi> hee
<pb facs="tcp:1223:8"/>was ſworne aſwel to the keeping of thoſe lawes and bringing in of no new, as the ſubiects vvere, &amp; if hee brake his othe, they vvere quit of all obedience. This appeareth in <hi>Forma iuramenti,</hi> vvhich hee toke at his Ioyous entraunce.</p>
            <p>This othe &amp; Lavv vvas broken by bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging in a nevv lavv of Inquiſition, vvhich tended to the vtter ſuppla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of the Prince and ſtates of the country, vvhich notvvythstanding they endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a ſeaſon, vſing al dutiful meanes by complaints made from the counſell &amp; ſtates at diuers &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry times, as are to be ſeene, but coulde haue no redreſſe in deede, though oftentimes they had faire promiſes. VVhen iustice could not be had by vvay of iuſt complaint from the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell &amp; States: the Prince &amp; States toke the maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the lavv into their ovvne hands, and ſo retaine it by Iuſtice, reſeruing the auncient liberties &amp; lavves to the benefite of all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playneth of wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g done
<pb facs="tcp:1223:9"/>vnto him, but the will of that Prince who woulde his will shoulde preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt Law to the ſubuerſion of the whole ſtate, as appeareth in their Records.</p>
            <p>Therfore this maintenaunce of law by the Prince of Orenge, is right, againſt the breaker of Lawe and bringer in of Tyrannie, the Spaniſh kinge. They ſay, bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in of Tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny &amp; breaker of Law, for that contrary to his oth, wherby both he &amp; all the Erles of Holland &amp; Zela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haue bin receiued into <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; no otherwyſe but vpon thoſe condicions limitted to them by their ſaid oth, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth the whole ſtate of gouernmente, leaueth no law but his own wil, &amp; ſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf, as though he had neuer bin ſworne, nor taken the countries vvith condicion, but had entred as an abſolute conquerour: Farre inferiour therin to Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; barbarous Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. VVe read of Cyrus the greate Monarche of the Eaſte, that aboue all his ſinguler ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which purchaſed him ſo greate a
<pb facs="tcp:1223:9"/>Fame as euer any Prince had, hee had this in him, that he ſuffered all Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnder his Monarchie to enioye their owne Lawes, customes, liberties &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and made no alteration againſt their wills. The like we finde recorded of Alexander the Greate, who vſed himſelfe after the ſame ſort in all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, contenting him onely with the Soueraignties ouer <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which he ſubdued, without any alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their Estate. And did not the auncient Romaynes walke after the ſame ſorte, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſubdued any Nation to their obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? Did they euer alter the ſtate, of any cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try which they conquered, &amp; enforce their people to receiue their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and Religion? VVhat courſe vſed <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> in his Conquests of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Did he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g any one iote of the ſtate of thoſe Citties which he conquered?</p>
            <p>Thus was the behauiour of thoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Princes, euen in their Conquests. ſuch moderation and equitie vſed they
<pb facs="tcp:1223:10"/>eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the middes of their fire &amp; ſword.</p>
            <p>The kinge of Spaine came not in by force, he was receyued by curteſie, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued as a Patrone and Protectour of their liberties, and vpon this condition onely, had the Seigniories giuen him, as to his predeceſſours before him, that hee should keepe thoſe Lawes and liberties ſafe &amp; ſound, by vertue of which, &amp; for preſeruation wherof they cast vpon him the Erledom, as they had don in former times vpon his auncesters. Vppon this condition he toke it, &amp; to this conditi he ſwore, as all his au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſters did, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; yelding himſelfe to the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour that other had incurred before him, &amp; by whoſe fall his aunceſters came into that preferment, if he committed the like treſpaſſe against the ſtates. To this, (I ſay) he was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by oth, let him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be demaunded, if he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denie it, they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to ſtand to the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the world, as falſaccuſers of ſo mighty a Prince, in charging him wyth
<pb facs="tcp:1223:10"/>periurie, a most horrible crime both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God &amp; man. But hee wil not, hee doth not denie it, it is confeſſed of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and published by Print in his owne books, vnder his owne Priuiledge. How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth his caſe &amp; theirs? was he not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by oth to obſerue their lawes? And in caſe he or any of his officers &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters did not obſerue but breake theim, did he not expreſly charge &amp; enioyne al his ſubiects by the ſame oth to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance against him &amp; them, and in no wyſe to yeld him any obedience, vntil he ſtoode and yelded to the fulfilling of his othe? The matter, as I ſayde, is to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, books impri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnder his owne Priuiledge vouch it to all the vvorlde. And shall they that ſtand for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of a law ſo iustly, being further charged thereto by the kings owne oth, be notvvithstandinge deemed for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels? Surely if there be no more than ſo, wee haue no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to eſteme or iudge
<pb facs="tcp:1223:11"/>of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might do no more, if either the kings auctority ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvere ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, or they had contrary to all right of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, made reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there, where they ought to haue shewed all obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. But as the vvorld is not able to charge them vvith the one, ſo the king I ſuppoſe will not chaleng vnto himſelf the other. VVe finde recorded by all that are lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as vvell heathen as Chriſtians, as vvell in lavves of the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles as in the lavves of God: that it is one thing to be <hi>Princeps ſupremus,</hi> a Superiour &amp; highest gouernour: &amp; an other thing to be <hi>Seni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or abſolutus,</hi> an abſolute lord. The one im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth a ſoueraintie &amp; chieftie of all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are within one liſt of lavv, as the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt miniſter of the lavv, but yet he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vvithin the compaſſe of the ſame lavv: the other noteth a perſon vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the compaſſe of al iuriſdiction, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller of all men, &amp; to be controlled of none. VVhoſo vvould chaleng this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter point to be the right of the kings ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title
<pb facs="tcp:1223:11"/>in thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryes, (I meane, that he would make him an abſolute Lord &amp; not a Supreme and higheſt Gouernoure,) hee should greatly diſcredite his honour in taking his othe. For force any perſonne what ſoeuer he bee, to take an othe and not to mynde to keepe it, is in that degree of dishonoure, as carryeth wyth it an impietie against GOD himſelfe, and ingendreth a iuste ſuſpicion in all men that shall haue to deale with him: for who would contract with that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any ſorte, that can &amp; will make ſo ſmall accompte of that, which hee hath called God himſelfe to witnes of, &amp; vowed to his Maieſtie to keepe, in the preſence of the Angels. I can not thinck ſo euill of the honour of a Prince, as that he would enter into ſo greate impietie: I iudge honourably of the Kinge of Spaine, and therefore I may not deeme, that he was of the Nature of that wicked Heathen, that ſayd for excuſe of himſelfe, in a caſe of like quality. <hi>Lingua iuraui, mentem iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuratam
<pb facs="tcp:1223:12"/>gero:</hi> I ſvvore wyth my tongue, ſo that my tongue ſtandeth bounde by othe, but I cary a minde and hart about me that hath not ſworne, ne ſtandeth ſo tyed. Be it farre from any Christian, to haue ſo euill an opinion of any Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wee haue not ſo to thincke of any Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, vnleſſe we heare him ſpeake and protest ſo, as that wretched caitife did. VVe ſee euidently by his ovvne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; teſtimonie of all the world, that ſuch an oth he toke, and the honourable opinion that we oughte to conceyue of the Maieſtie of a Kinge muste needes perſvvade vs, that hee meant them as he ſwore. As he ſwore (I ſay) when hee in the ſame article exempted them from all obedience, and armed them that should attempte ought to the contrary: If hee ſvvore this, and mente this, then are they no rebelles, in fulfillinge that, vvhich hee charged them vppon theyr othes.</p>
            <p>But vvhat ſaye they, that vvil (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithstandinge)
<pb facs="tcp:1223:12"/>iustifie the Kings do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges and blame the ſubiectes with ſo greeuous a crime. For no one iote of that that is aforeſayd can be denyed. They ſaye that the Pope, who hath from GOD <hi>Plenitudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſtatis,</hi> Fulnes of povver, did diſpenſe vvith him from this othe. Firste if that bee ſo, that the Pope hath freed him from his othe, then hath hee by the ſame facte freed them from their obedience: for they vvere in no wyſe, nor by vertue of any title ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to him, but by vertue and title of his othe. Take the grounde of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection avvay, and they are not ſubiect but free.</p>
            <p>But vvhether it he ſo or no, that the Pope hath throughe his abſolute power, (which he calleth <hi>Plenitudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> fulnes of povver) freed him from that othe, I knovv not: onely this I know, that the Biſhop of <hi>Arras,</hi> aftervvard Cardinal of <hi>Granuile</hi> gaue him ſuche Counſell, &amp; ſayd the Pope should do ſo. And if it
<pb facs="tcp:1223:13"/>followed ſo in effect, as it may be wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectured by the ſequel, (for no doubte a king would not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo ſtoutly to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence &amp; maintenaunce of ſuch impietie against God &amp; man, as periurie is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he had ſome better ground &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante) this wilbe a Caueat, and a leſſon for all Princes &amp; States to teach them to bevvare howe they deale anye more with the kinge of Spaine, or any other that giueth ſuch credite to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope. For what aſſurance ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue of all their Contracts and Leagues that paſſe and are made betwene them, if the othes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, may be diſpenſed withall at the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes pleaſure? That were nothing els in deede and effecte, but to bring all true Christian Kinges and Princes, vvhich make conſcience and put a Religion in the bretch of their othes, into bondage &amp; ſlauery: to make them ſerue the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and profite of the other Romishe kinge: vvho mindeth no further to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his, then shall ſtande vvith his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite,
<pb facs="tcp:1223:13"/>or pleaſure of that higher power of Rome. If the caſe ſtand ſo, what faults ſoeuer Princes haue committed in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time in this behalf, I doubt not but they wilbe wyſer and more circumſpect hereafter. I meane they will make no leagues nor take anye othes of the Pope ☜ or any Princes and States of his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, ſeing they haue ſo plaine a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in this caſe, that their othes may &amp; shalbe diſpenſed wythall, when and how ofte ſoeuer they liſte. I ſuppoſe there vvas ſuch a clauſe in the Contract that vvas made vvith the kinge of Spayne for the mariage of Queene Mary, that he should not alter or chaunge any one iote of the Lawes and Customes aſwel publike as priuate of the Realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, if he had broken this braunch, &amp; vouched the equity of his dealing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, vppon a licence &amp; diſpenſation from the Pope, I doubt ſore whether the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and States of England would haue taken that for good payment: I doubte
<pb facs="tcp:1223:14"/>I ſay, vvhether the Nobility and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Englande, would haue ſuffered him vnder that cloake, to haue bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed all the Lavves of Englande and brought in the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Millan</hi> or <hi>Naples?</hi> I doubt, vvhether the Nobles and people of England would haue bin acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted rebels for vvithstanding ſuch breatch of Contract. I doubt, vvhether they vvould haue ſuffred him ſo quietly to haue caryed awaye the Crowne from the Queenes Maiestie to haue ſet it v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his Spaniards heads? And yet hee might as iuſtly haue done that, as this, if this rule be good. VVe may thanck God we are deliuered from him, wee cannot tell what he woulde haue done, thoughe wee may ſurmiſe by this preſident, what he might haue pretended. I tell you, this excuſe of periurie may ſeeme reaſonable to them that are of his Court, for ſuch a God they haue: but it is a perillous preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for vs, vnleſſe wee bevvare of it. If it ſeeme a good plea for king Philip to
<pb facs="tcp:1223:14"/>ſay, he hath not broken his othe herein, becauſe the Pope diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed with him, what maye all Princes that haue made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts with him loke for, but iuſte quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell againſte themſelues to be reuenged both with fire and ſvvord, when ſoeuer the Pope shall liſt to diſpenſe? And I am afrayde the benefite of this diſpenſation wilbe vſed, if at any time they may haue oportunity (which God forbid) for <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Q. Ma. &amp; the realm of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as they ſay, ſtand exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat: if ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all oth is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed withall, you know that very well. How be it if Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe God &amp; conſcience, shall iudge this dealing to be good, &amp; if they can ſo eaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that ſuch maner of dalying with othes, is Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, ſurely then wil I as they ſay &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> the K. of Spaine hath right, and the Prince of Orenge &amp; States of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land &amp; Zelande haue wronge, that his bretch of oth, law &amp; custome, is lawful, &amp; they in withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it, are rebels &amp; traitours.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:15"/>
            <p>But if they shall iudge with the truth, as truth is in deede, that no mortall man can diſpenſe with an othe that bindeth the conſcience of man, for it is a matter within the iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God alone, &amp; againe, if they shal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider this wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, that all the righte and title that the King of Spaine hath to thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes is onely by vertue of this othe and no otherwyſe, ſo that his ſuperioritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth but by way of Stipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if hee performe thoſe conditions, (for hee hath no better title then all his predeceſſours had) then will they eaſelie reſolue, that there is great fault in that pretence, yea very preiudicious and an euill preſidente to all Princes that haue to contract vvyth him: &amp; on the other ſide, that the Prince and the States do in iustice and equitie both before God and man what they do: and are not to be charged with theſe greeuous termes of Rebels and Traytours.</p>
            <p>NOVV for our owne caſe, (ſay they
<pb facs="tcp:1223:15"/>that like of that parte) it is good to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member for the neceſsitie, what neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours we haue &amp; what mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours haue: vvhat affections haue bin vttered, in ſubſcriptions to the Counſel or conſpiracie of Trent, wherin the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all Protestant Princes (&amp; namely of <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Queene &amp; Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land (haue bin determined: vvhat pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes haue bin vſed &amp; furthered to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed title of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petitrice of her Maieſties crowne: what intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces entred with the rebels of England: what ayds promiſed to them in their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall rebellion: how the rebels haue bin receiued, ſuccoured and releeued wyth penſions, &amp; maintayned there, ſithens their ouerthrowe here: what letters of Marck or diſguiſed Pyracie againſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish ſubiectes grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to <hi>Don Thomas Coppley,</hi> graund Lorde of the Maze, Gatten, Roughey, and of many otherga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſounds of petie titles, &amp; ſuch other little fellowes, beſides Stories Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb facs="tcp:1223:16"/>How in thoſe dominions daily boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes haue bin published with open war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, priuiledge, and allowaunce most ſlaunderous to the Queene, and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous against her state: How the traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Papists are there vpholden in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and dignitie, who doubte not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to affirme, that he cannot erre that hath pronounced our Queene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued: what deuiſes haue bin vſed by one Embaſsadour, a holy biſhop, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Aquila, against her Maiestie and her Counſell: How by an other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsadour De Speſe, lewde and vncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly letters haue bin written vnder ſaucy ſignes of the names of <hi>Oriane Amadis,</hi> and ſuch vnprincely toyes, audaciouſly to reatch at the honour of ſuch a moste vertuous, high &amp; noble Queene: Howe the ſame rashe perſonage hath not bin miſliked there for his ſo doing: How the <hi>Bull</hi> of her Maiesties depriuation, &amp; of the aſsoyling of her ſubiects fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their alle giau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, hath bin printed, ſpred abroade,
<pb facs="tcp:1223:16"/>ſet vpon posts, &amp; magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to knowledge in the low Countryes remayninge vnder that Princes rule: How in Spaine it ſelf, her Ma ſubiects are daily take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; impriſoned, manacled tormented &amp; exquiſitely murdered in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte of her Maiesties honour, and <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> ſafe freedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mutual trafique: How <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is permitted dayly to rage againſt Englishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for praying to God euen on Seabord, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the lawes of the Church of England: Howe the Prince excuſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by ſaying he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not diſobey the Church. And must he obey the Church, in following their ſentence that the Queene of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is depriued of her Crowne? The euident apparence that he lacketh onely opportunity to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade England: a thing most apt for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his conquest, and a thing most needefull for him, wherewith to reteyne the rest of his owne.</p>
            <p>One most vrgent neede, not to haue him to ſtrong. One moſt important pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy,
<pb facs="tcp:1223:17"/>to hold warre farther of, rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to draw it home. Infinite are both the reaſons &amp; occaſions that this cauſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth.</p>
            <p>For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, behold (ſay they) the fruitful land: the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Sea by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the neerenes of the Contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to hold our warres, or do diſpleaſures far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of from England: the rule of trade both of the riuer of Rhene, and land of Germany: the commodities paſsing that vvay both for Marchandiſe and Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: as Cables, Pitch, Tarre, Mastes &amp; other matter for Shippes, to be plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to ourſelues, &amp; ſcarce to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes at oure pleaſures, the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe &amp; ſafety of the trade of our mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants euery where. But of theſe profits there is no end. And among other this is the greatest, that they vvill not (like Ireland) be chargeable, but a most Noble encreaſe of reuenevves to the Crovvne, able at their ovvne charge to defende themſelues vnder her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſties
<pb facs="tcp:1223:17"/>name &amp; protection, and to ſerue the Realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: a Nauie ioyned with her Maieſties Nauie, and mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners able to hold and driue from Sea all Princes in Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dom. Finally Safety, Riches, Stre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and honour.</p>
            <p>For right, their offers (ſay they) make it apparent both by diſcent in her Ma. (if the holder againſt his oth vvil ſtand vpon diſcent alone): electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breach of othes &amp; pacts: on tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte rightfull conquest vppon iuſt cauſes, for ſo manifeſt iniuries &amp; perils: a conquest I ſay, yet with a ſweete and eaſye yoke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people willing to receiue it. For facility, is to be marked (ſaye they) their owne offer, the readineſſe of the people to embrace, their owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the to haue ſtand thus long alone, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting of the aduerſary, &amp; all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opportunities, delyuered by God him ſelf. And to all theſe good meanes, the moste glorious acte to releue the Church of God against Papists, the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators
<pb facs="tcp:1223:18"/>and enemyes of publike naturall and Christen fayth, the great meane to appeaſe the controuerſies of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for Religion.</p>
            <p>Adde alſo the noble pollicy &amp; fitnes, to enter into vniuerſal league of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians against the Pope &amp; Popish con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies: the aide of ſo noble a Prince, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of Orenge, ſo able, ſo worthy and ſo likely a man to ſerue Christendom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Empire of the Turcke, &amp; ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Rome: the greedy ioye of her Maiesties people to follow her pleaſure in purſuing of ſuch a noble enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what I haue heard ſay on all ſides: I leaue to you the iudgment of all theſe conceits: I leaue to Counſellers the gouerning of vs all by the beſt adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and directions: who (I doubt not in their wiſedoms) do ſee the beſt: &amp; in this Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lack no help of conſent &amp; ſinewes, that this Realme ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue. And I leaue to God the guidinge of harts &amp; ſucceſſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:18"/>
            <p>But beſide all that I haue noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of other, this you shall take as mine owne full beleuing: that it is not in our will to haue peace by letti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them alone, when the aduerſary tarieth but to ſubdue them, that he may aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce himſelf agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt vs. But to hold warre fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of, both in place and time is novv offered to her Maiesties Election. Peace ſhe cannot haue ſure, by peace.</p>
            <p>And one notable matter I hear of: they be moſt deſirous <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> England will receiue them: but rather then they will returne to their old thraldome, they will creepe vnder the yoke, euen of the Muſcouite or Turke himſelfe. Much rather will they yeld them to Fraunce, that hath now ſo many armies ready to take hold of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reiect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That conſequence may proue ill for vs: And I do not take it certaine that Fraunce shall for euer haue ciuill warres. It maye be that God after the bloud of ſo many Martirs, wil giue peace to his Church in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. You
<pb facs="tcp:1223:19"/>ſee ther is but one life betwene them &amp; the ſucceſsiue raigne of many tollerabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. If God should bereaue the world of the preſent French king ſodenly, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe bleſſe Fraunce wyth an other or that the Kinge of neceſsity yelde to a firme peace: How eaſly vpon our refuſal vvill the alliaunce of the Prince of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge wyth the houſe of Fraunce, draw Holland and Zeland to Fraunce. O merueylous aduauncement of Fraunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by ſea and land! Shall they be lords o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Trafique, Lords of furniture, of Shippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lords of great &amp; many shippes &amp; goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> harborowes, &amp; (that most is) ſo greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo neere vs? I pray God it neuer be, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be ſo daungerous.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1223:19"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>IKE AS in time paſte, oure aduerſaries haue alwayes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning pickte quarrels againſt our cauſe, with intente to procure a greater miſlike thereof in all mennes mindes, and to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte haue framed many fayned ſlaunders, in layinge to our charge, that wee are not onely fallen awaye from the fayth, but alſo become rebells againſt the Maieſtie of the Kinge of <hi>Spaine</hi> oure ſoueraigne and naturall Prince, to thende that vnder the ſhadowe of ſuch fine coulours, they mighte both blemiſhe the eyes of the ſimple ſorte which are altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norante of the cauſe, and alſo ſeeme cloſely to couer their owne diſordinate greedines of gaine, euen to the face of the wyſeſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they bee the better acquainted wyth thoſe affayres: Euen ſo wee aſcertaine oure ſelues, that they will not ſticke (by all meanes they maye) hereafter likewyſe to practiſe the drowninge and vtter ſuppreſſinge of all ſuch true dealing, as doth nowe but begin by litle and litle to come to lighte. They publiſhe and proclaime, (althoughe moste vntrulye) that wee are the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that will giue no eare to any agreemente, be it neuer ſo reaſonable:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1223:20"/>and that we endeuour our ſelues to ſeeke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but how we may maintayn this ciuil diſſention and dangerous warres within oure owne booſome, although it procure the vtter deſtruction of this our poore Country: and all for oure pleaſure (they ſay,) becauſe wee are minded to bend our wills &amp; appetits to croſſe his Maieſtie. Thus do they ſtill cauil. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to thend that none may hereafter by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to light credit to their falſe reports, ſo much abuſe themſelues, as to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne thoſe that are innocentes, and to iuſtifie ſuch as bee moſt cruell enemies to iuſtice: VVee thought it moſt neceſſary (after many ſupplications at diuers &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry times exhibited vnto his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie) yet once againe to publiſh this our last requeſt made vnto him, &amp; therwithall to lay before your eyes, all ſuch meanes as haue bin made on our parte for the appeaſinge of this warre, as ye may moſt plainly perceiue by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch letters, as haue bin written on ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part to that effect, without adding or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing any thing therin, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that euery man may iudge without any ſuſpicion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truth of the matter. Meaning thereby moſt manifeſtly to ſhow forth, both in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyeth the originall cauſe &amp; beginning of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1223:20"/>this warre, &amp; alſo who is moſt to be blamed, for that we attaine not vnto a perfecte peace and vnity. Moreouer, that we haue alwayes acknowledged the kinge of Spaine to be oure Soueraigne Prince and liege Lord, as one gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs of God to rule and gouerne vs with all iuſtice and equity, according to ſuch contractes as we weare both bound vnto, and according to ſuch aunciente Rights, Vſages, Liberties, and Priuiledges, as hee hath bin most ſolemply ſworne vnto: and that we haue alwayes had our recourſe vnto him most hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and with al due reuerence. For albeit that ſome pretending a fayned deſire of quietnes and vnity in our Country, haue priuately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded vs, that in oure treaty of peace, wee must looke eſpecially to the obſeruing of two points, that is to witte, that respect of the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Maiesty of the King be kept moste inuiolable, and that in anye wyſe no mention be made of the alteringe of Religion: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we haue had most euident proofes to perſwade vs, that this is not the way to mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the mortall hatred of oure enemies, but rather to encreaſe and ſharpen it: Yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe wee haue in all pointes behaued oure ſelues ſo reaſonably, and wyth ſo great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1223:21"/>as euen our enemies them ſelues cannot accuſe vs (and ſay truly) but that we haue in all pointes obſerued a dutifull order, as moste plainly ſhall appeare by the diſcourſe followi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Conſidering that wee haue franckly remitted the whole iuſtice of our cauſe, vnto the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his Maieſtie, &amp; the generall eſtates of our Countrie. Hoping that they, both beinge better acquainted with our eſtate, &amp; alſo bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affectioned, both to the King and countrye then Straungers can bee: mighte the rather haue both the meanes &amp; the will, to giue ſuch counſell vnto the king, as may be moſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of a perfect peace &amp; vnitie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, and laſt of all, for ſetting our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try in her auncient proſperitie. Hereuppon our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries (contrary to our expectacion) haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued themſelues with ſuche parcialitie, as they woulde not once ſo much as haue any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde or reſpecte vnto our requeſt made vnto his Maieſtie, but vſurpi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſoueraigne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Country, they haue cleane depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his Maieſtie from all libertie of Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and according to their owne appetite &amp; will, cleane barred oure cauſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all knowledge of Iuſtice, of ſet purpoſe to hinder all concorde.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1223:21"/>And that haue they done principally (as they themſelues confeſſe) for becauſe we haue vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the generall aſſembly of the Eſtates, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch beyonde all memorie of man, hath alwayes ben vſed heretofore amongſt our auncitours and Predeceſſours. Beſides this, to make their malice more manifeste, they haue euer ſince committed greater cruelties in burning and ſcorchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſuch as were of our Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they did before. Moreouer, they haue ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in all the reſt of the Eſtates of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try with threatnings &amp; force, of purpoſe to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerue their turne towards thexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nical appetites. VVherby it appeareth moſt plainly, that they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with hauing once raiſed this great blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy warre to the preiudice of his Maieſtie, &amp; vtter deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Country: but do ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour themſelues to procede with their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous deuiſes, to thend they may ſubdue the Countrie at their owne pleaſure, and bring it into perpetuall ſeruitude &amp; bondage. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer wheras they make ſhew at ſome times, of a deſire to entre into ſome treaty with vs of agreement: they do not pretend that to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, but onely to deceaue vs, and by ſuch a fayned diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to hold the other Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1223:22"/>and Villages in ſome good hope, that they may not ioyne themſelues with vs to reſiste their tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, hoping that by this meanes they may come to their purpoſe, Like as they haue already procured in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by their vndirect and priuie practiſes. But ſuch is our truſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bountifull mercy of our good God, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue bin ſo myraculouſly defended hitherto fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wicked enterpriſes, as wee not onely hope to eſcape fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daunger of their diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh deuiſes, but alſo that all people &amp; nations of Christendome, all Kings &amp; Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates, and eſpecially the Maiesty imperiall with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours &amp; Princes of the Empire, ſeing here by moſt clerely our faithfull and ſincere hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, &amp; our moſt ſure and certaine equity, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with our ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſire to attaine to peac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and vnity, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring the ſame with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful pride &amp; cruell tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: will yeld vnto vs their indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fauour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and maintaine the iuſtice of oure cauſe by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient meanes they may. And if peradui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it fall out hereaſter, that we be forced by the vniuſt &amp; vnreaſonable procedings of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aduerſaries, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt our willes to ſeeke &amp; ſerch for ſom other relief more to our aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſafety, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue don heretofore: we hope
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1223:22"/>that euen then they will not impute the fault thereof vnto vs, but vnto oure enemies, who haue forced vs therunto. VVherof we require all and euery perſon by maner of proteſtacion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be aduertiſed herein, that we only haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto the Iuſtice, equity, &amp; wiſedom of the moſt high, and renowmed Maieſty of the Emperour, &amp; to all the moſt noble and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Electours and Princes of the Empyre of Almaigne, together with all the potentates of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, that they may take ſome care of our cauſe, &amp; not giue credit or hearing vnto the ſlanderous reports of our aduerſaries, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider ſomwhat neerer the indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of our cauſe &amp; mainteigne the ſame, ſo farre forth, as duty to God &amp; the world doth require. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wee do aduiſe all the Eſtates of theſe Lowe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider herein as it were in a glaſſ what eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our enemies make of them, &amp; withall to imagine how they determine to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them, if their deuiſes take ſuch effecte as they do deſire. VVherefore let them beware that for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of courage or other occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſuffer not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be abuſed by their fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and double dealinges, Altho they make ſhewe of a feruente affection for the perfecte peace &amp; quietnes of oure Conutry. But rather hauinge regarde vnto their tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1223:23"/>call euill meaninges, which they beare in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall vnto the Eſtates of our Country. Let them reſolue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, couragiouſly to reſiſte ſuch inſolencies, and call to minde both their othe and dutie that they owe to their Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try and by all induſtrie ſeeke the maintenance of the good and lawfull rights, contracts aend li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of their foreſaide country. In the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherof, they ſhall not only do a good deede in their life time, but alſo leaue vnto their poſterity a good report to their immortal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Now then to thende you may the better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theffect of the letters folowing, and the ground of all the matter: You muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed, that at ſuche time as <hi>Mounſieur Philip</hi> of <hi>Marnix,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mounſieur</hi> of <hi>Mont Sai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Aldego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy,</hi> being priſoners at <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> had (by the licence and commaundement of <hi>Mounſieur</hi> of <hi>Noircarmes</hi>) written diuers &amp; ſondry times vnto the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> as touchinge the meanes to enter into ſome communication for finiſhing of theſe preſent warres: the matter was brought to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as that after the death of the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Seig.</hi> of <hi>Noircarmes,</hi> the perſons were nominated, which were to be imployed in this matter. But in the meane time happened the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1223:23"/>ouerthrow of <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Ludovvyk,</hi> and for that cauſe it ſeemed not good vnto the great Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundador, to proceede any further herein: alledging that thereby, the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of the King ſhoulde be ſomewhat dymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Neuertheles the ſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundador wiſhed and aduiſed all the townes of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> to addreſſe them ſelues vnto the King by maner of ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to this end, that the effect of the agreement which mighte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thereof, mighte be attributed rather vnto the bountye, and liberalitye of the Kinge, than to any righte or equitye that we mighte looke for of dutye. This Kinde of dealing was cauſe ſufficient, why this treaty ceaſſed, vntill ſuche tyme as <hi>Mounſieur de Champaign,</hi> ſent a letter vnto <hi>Mounſieur Charles de Boiſot</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Mydleburch,</hi> the tenure whereof follweth her-afterword forword, with an anuſwere the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof made by his Brother <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur Lois de Boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſot,</hi> being marked with. A. and. B. But vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that he was abſent by reaſon that he was ſent of a meſſage into <hi>England</hi> from his excellency, he thought beſt, him ſelf to make a voyage vnto <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> whether it were to aſſiſt his brother in lawe <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the Coente <hi>de la Roche</hi> towardes the obteyning of a pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1223:24"/>publiſhed as him ſelf ſayd, or for ſome other pryuate affayres of his owne, I know not. But this I am ſure of, that when he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me thither, he talked at landge of the matters aforeſayd with <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur de Sainct Aldegond</hi> who remayned then priſoner, as with one whome he fownd yet ſtill ſo affected to the furthera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce of our peace, as that he requeſted moſte earneſtly, that notwythſtanding the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before reherſed, yet the purſute of a thinge ſo neceſſary for our publique weal might not be left of vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche a ſoden. Herein, he made promiſe on the behalf of the Prince of <hi>Ore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge</hi> and of the Eſtates of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> that they would rather be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to leeſe ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me parte of their owne right, than ſeek to vſurpe any thing vpon the Kings Maieſtie, for the which cauſe it was thought good to ymploy the forenamed priſoner, who preſently was ſent to <hi>Roterda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> towards his excellency, to treat vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exchaunge of priſoners, to thend that ther with all he might woorke ſomme good effect in the matters before reherſed. Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that he tooke great regard to the auct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hority of the King, and that no poynts of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion weare in any wiſe mencioned It hapned alſo that <hi>Signeor Ian de Mattenes, Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1223:24"/>de la Rinicre</hi> and the <hi>Aduocat Treſlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me a litle befor this, by lyce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alſo vnto <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> for certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> particuler affaires, as thei ſaid &amp; had by &amp; by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto them a ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chdarge to deale with his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, &amp; with the foreſaid Eſtates, touching ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me good meane of pacification. The aunſwere that theis eſtates gaue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> followeth hereafter, woord by woord, and is marked with the. C. But as it appeareth, this aunſuere pleaſed not <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire de Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pagni.</hi> Wherefore during the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode of <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſier de S. Aldegonde</hi> as yet in <hi>Rotterda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> he wrote a letter vnto him to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me effect, declaring therein his minde more at large This letter likewiſe followeth in order, and is marked with D. hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yt followed that <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſier de. S. Aldego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> treated yet ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what furtherwith the foreſayd Eſtates in ſuch erneſt ſorte, as that they weare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to make their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the Kings Ma. in forme of ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with owt attributi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the name of the Eſtats there vnto, which of duti belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vn to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and alſo with owt making any mecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any point of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but only requeſting moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly that it wold pleaſe his Ma. to ſet order in al things by his owne anothoriti and by the general aduice of the eſtates, but firſt that it would pleaſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1223:25"/>him to cauſe all the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers which troubled the conutrye to auoyde from thence: ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in all things beſids to any ſuche order as his Maitſtie, and the Eſtates generall ſhoulde thinck moſte meete for them (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by ther requeſt) which is marked with the letter. E. the which requeſt the forenamed <hi>Mounſieur de S. Aldegond</hi> caried him ſelf vnto <hi>Mounſieur de Champagini</hi> to <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort,</hi> yelding him ſelf agayne in to his priſon at <hi>Vtrecht.</hi> But with in a while after, <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pagni</hi> hauing bene at the court in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> ſent backe the foreſayd requeſt vnto <hi>Mounſieur Iunius</hi> Gouernour of the <hi>Vere,</hi> who together with <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur de Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> had remayned in hoſtage at <hi>Mountſort</hi> for <hi>Mounſiur de S. Aldegond</hi> during his abſence, and by that meanes alſo were admyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur de Champagni</hi> to treat of this matter, as may well appeare by a letter he ſent to <hi>Mounſire Iuniꝰ</hi> which followeth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewiſe marked with. F. wherupon the ſayd <hi>Iunius</hi> made him an aunſwere by writing agayne, as appeareth with the markes of G. and H. We leaue the reſt vnto the good reader to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of, deſyring God te geue vs the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that all may redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto his glorye, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1223:25"/>edifying of his Churche.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="A" type="letter">
            <head>A. To Mounſire' M. Charles Boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, my very freend.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſire Boiſot:</hi> the great league of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytie which hathe been betwene <hi>M. de Granuill</hi> and <hi>M. Threſorier</hi> our fathers (whome God pardon) the frendeſhip of the Cardynall my brother, and myne owne goodwil towardes you, which ſtill I obſerue inuiolable with my Ladies your ſiſters, and with all the reſt of your free<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des here, haue cauſed me oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes to be ſorye for your abſence, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for your troubles. Now therefore ſythence that his Maieſtie at this preſent ſheweth a great deſier of the peace and tranquillitye of theſe lowe countries, and a great affection that all ſuche as haue abſented them ſelues from his fauour, ſhould returne agayne vnto his good grace (the which thing I aſſure you I haue both wiſhed for long, and alſo procured to my power, in all tymes and places conuenient for that purpoſe:) and ſynce that I my ſelf by the appoyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his excellency, am come vn
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1223:26"/>
               <hi>Vtrecht</hi> of purpoſe to conferre with my Brother in lawe <hi>Mounſire' de la Roche,</hi> touching the bringing home againe of theis loſte ſheepe: All theis things, and our old frend ſhip conſidered, I thought good to write vnto you, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that throwgh your furtheraunce aunſwering to my well meaning, we might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour owrſelues to deliuer this poore cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntre from thoſe great miſeries, which we ſe embra ſe it on euery ſide: promiſing vnto you by the faith of an honeſt man and tru free<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne my ſelf to the vttermoſte of my power the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein, and to procure for you (if you doe here any notable ſeruice towardes the bringing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganie of this people to the obedience of his Maieſtie) not only a full reſtitucion of that which was yours, but alſo peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture a good reward, and this dothe he will me to offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you vpon ſo good a grownde, as (in myne opinion) neither you ought to refuſe, nor the Townes which are reuolted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſeruice, to omytt. And if I had any meanes to conferre with you, I woulde not doubt, but wee two ſhoulde make ſo good an entrance into thoſe matters, as that not only your ſelf and thoſe townes, but alſo agreat many of others, ſhould finde better fruit thereof, then youe wolde
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1223:26"/>thinck for. I haue fownde bothe better acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and creditt then I can tell you by writing, and alſo a ſinguler bownty in the Gouernour that now is, at all tymes when any ſpeache hapneth betwene him and me touching the appeaſing of thoſe callamities, vnto the which I pray you to geue eare, and to accompany nay zeale with yours: which if you doe, I doubt not but (by the grace of God) we ſhall worke agreat good turne vnto this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale. <hi>M. Boiſott</hi> I recommend my ſelf hartely vnto you and commyt you to God, whome I pray, to ſende vnto you your harts deſyre, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs alla good end of all our afflictions.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cantecroi</hi> 
                  <date>this. 14. of Iune. 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Entirely your beſt frende <hi>I. Perrenot.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="B" type="letter">
            <head>B. To Mounſire M. Perrenot my very frende.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſire de Champagni</hi> your letters of the date of the. 14. of this mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth which you ſent to my brother, are hapned to my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, which in his abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I haue opened and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1223:27"/>red, reioyſing very muche to find therein the deſier that his Maieſtie: hathe now of the qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etnes of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, and that he would haue his ſubiectes return againe into his good fauour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which you ſay, that bothe he hath wiſhed fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſynce, and your ſelf haue procured to th'u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tmoſte of your power. Whereas you deſier to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my brother applye him ſelf (if it weare poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to the ioyning with you in zeale towarde the helping of his poore countrye out of thoſe myſeries, that on euery ſyde compaſſe it a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout, promyſing your aid and endeuour vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the othe of a ſyncere honeſte man and trew fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and that his Maieſtie dooth offer him no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only a reſtitution of his owne, but alſo a good rewarde, which courteſie, neyther he ſhall do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well in refuſing, neyther the reuolted Townes in reiecting: And whereas, you wiſhe for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſon to conferre withall, aſſuring him of the good hope you haue in the ſinguler bountye of this new gouernour: To all theis thinges my brother (if he were preſent) myght make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unſuere at large, with the conſent of the Prince of <hi>Orenge.</hi> But foraſmuche he is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I wil ſay no more, but that this zeale of his Maieſtie, in deſyring the peace and quye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tnes of his ſubiectes, is a noble and worthie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1223:27"/>ſuche a Criſtian prynce as he is, and that no man wolde be gladder nor better content therewith than the Prince him ſelf, as at your comming to <hi>Vtrecht</hi> yowr ſelf ſhal ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well perceiue and vnderſtand by yowr brother in law the <hi>Conte de la Roche,</hi> whoe knoweth very well what hath already paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in communication hereof and alſo by letters written in that behalf. But this dare I ſay of myne owne hed, that in my ſimple iudgement there is no meanes to appeaſe theis troubles, but only by drawing of theis ſtraungers owt of owr countrye. For they are ſuche a kinde of people, as bothe by heareſay in tymes paſt, and by proofes in tymes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent we finde to be no men of their worde, nor ſuche whoſe promiſes any man may truſt. For alwaies they finde ſomme bypathes to eſcape by following therin the manner of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of <hi>Conſtans</hi> wherof they pratle daily. Wher vpon, I may conclude, that at their handes there can be no aſſuraunce looked for, ſo longe as they remayne in the countrye. I did ſend your letters vnto his Excel. to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he mighte bothe ſee and know the great deſire you ſay you haue of the wellfare of owr countrie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſting you <hi>M. Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pagni</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1223:28"/>good zeale that you pretend to beare to owr quyet. Prayng God to geue, vnto you the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your mynde, and vnto vs an eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of owr afflictions.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Mydleburche</hi> 
                  <date>this 17 of Iune. 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Entyrely your good frend, <hi>Lois de Boiſott.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="C" type="answer">
            <head>D. The aunſwere of the Eſtates to the Queſtions propounded.</head>
            <p>AS towching that which hathe ben propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto the Eſtates of <hi>Holland</hi> &amp; <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> concerning the troubles of this preſent warres, &amp; how to bring the ſame to a good &amp; ſure paſſe, for the reſt &amp; quyetnes of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, &amp; the ſaffety of his Maieſties ſubiectes: Theis Eſtates doe openly declare that they weare neuer of opinion, nor be at this preſent, of taking any weapons in hand, in any cauſe that mighte be preiudicial againſt his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, his countrye, or prouinces: but that they in acquitall of their bownden dutie and chardge, with intent to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue the reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1223:28"/>&amp; highnes of their ſeignories &amp; Lorde ſhips, together with their Priuileges, othes, rightes, worthy cuſtomes, and liberties of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri, and ſubiectes, haue been conſtrayned to with ſtand by mayne force, the harde Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tyrannie, &amp; violence of the duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> and of the ſtraungers his adherentes, who by vnaccuſtomed exactions and oppreſſions of the poore ſubiectes, haue troubled owr comon welth, not ſeeking for any thing els, than by their Inſolencie to make them ſelues Maſters of his Maieſties country &amp; ſubiectes: and by that meanes to bring them into perpetual bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, to the great preiudice bothe of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice &amp; of their maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as the fore ſaid Eſtates haue heretofore declared and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, in ſuche ſorte that they wil not at this preſent make any articles of pacificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his Maieſtie, whome they haue allwaies here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore ſought to obay and ſerue in all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye as their liege Lorde and Prince: but like humble ſuters, they requeſt that yt wil pleaſe his Maieſtie, like a good father to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vnto the pouerties &amp; afflicions of theis his lowe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, with a mercifull eye, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that they may bee brought againe to vnitie, quiett, and libertye, to traffique as they were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1223:29"/>wont to doe. The which, will bothe aduaunce the dignitie of him ſelf, &amp; encreaſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitye of his ſubiectes. And certenly this cannot be brought to paſſe: ſo longe as theis ſtraingers ſhalbe ſuffred to exerciſe their force, and tirannie, whoſe gaine and proffit dothe more conſiſt vpon troubles and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres, than in any good gouernment of the countrie. For they be ſuche perſons, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally are moſte ſludious of their owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer proffit. Loe here the ſpeciall cauſe and mocion of this warre. Wherfore it may pleaſe his Maieſtie: to cauſe theis ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to retyre them ſelues, and afterward by a franke communication together with the aduice of the generall eſtates of the countrie, dutifully aſſembled, to ſet ſo good order, pollecy, and gouernment amongſt vs, as that the Subiectes of his Maieſtie may from hencefoorth aſſure them ſelues from all perrils and inconueniences that may happen vnto them. And foraſmuche as (of wee may ſpeake franckly) noughte els can bee looked for, by the continewance of this warre, but only a diſpeopling, a ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynes, and an vtter Ruyne of all his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties countries in theis partes, ſpecially for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1223:29"/>becauſe that the more thinhabitantes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of doe geue them ſelues daylie to thexerciſe of Armes, cleane forgettinge and laying aſide their woonted traffique and trade of merchaundize: the leſſe good is to bee looked for at their hande: For wee ſe ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l to what lycentious lyues and liberties, ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are commonlye inclyned). By meane whereof it is to be feared, leaſt there will happen a moſte domageable and daungerous diminiſhing of all kinde of traffique and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundize, bothe by ſea and land, redown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vtter ſhaking of his Maieſties eſtates, or the ſlipping aſide of his ſeruice:) The ſaid Eſtates doe humbly requeſt, that better regarde bee had here vnto, ſo as bothe <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> and alſo their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces and contries adioyning, being by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritye of his Maieſtie in all partes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardged from the troubleſome multitude of foldiars and ſtraungers: all maner of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion and prouicion made for warres may preſently ſurceaſſe, and haue end on all ſides, in ſuche ſort as the natural inhabitants of the countries may once againe be ſetled in ſome ſurety, &amp; the one being reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled, to thother, may with free libertye talke and traffique
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1223:30"/>together. This ſuite being obteined, the ſaid Eſtates doe promiſe on their partes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in all pointes the Dutyes of good and faithfull Subiectes, hoping that the letters, of the great Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dador, and all other faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vaſſalles and ſeruauntes to his Maieſtie, will herein put to their helping hand, the which we doe requeſt and pray with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and humility.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="D" type="letter">
            <head>D. To Mounſire' M. de Sainct Aldegondi.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MOunſiere de Mont S. Aldegonde</hi> wee maruell not a litle, that all this while we haue not herd any thing from you. Yeſterday there arriued here <hi>M. de la Rinicre,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Aduocate Treslonge:</hi> whoe vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſomme priuate affaires went to <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam,</hi> where they did aſſay certein meanes touching the appeaſing of theis preſent troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, following therein no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I permitted them to doe. But vpon certain queſtions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pownded of them of that ſide vnto <hi>M. de Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicre,</hi> they grew into farther talke of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at their owne pleaſure, being moued there
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1223:30"/>vnto (as I gheſſe) by a feruent zeale they had to doe their countrie good. But the retorne of their aunſwere groweth nothing nere to any quyetnes. Wherefore you can not make me beleeue that you deſier to haue peace, to the obteyning whereof you promiſed me fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ymploy your ſelf. For neither can the title that they take vpon them, as appeareth by that writing which was broughte vnto me, bee ſo vſurped by them: neither ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which they alledge for their reuolting, be admitted by any means, for that they touch to neere the reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Maieſtie, althoughe they ſay they woulde mainteigne the ſame, wherein I finde no reaſon. And as touching the meanes that they make, they are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſuch reſpectes as I hoped for. It ſeemeth by their ſpeaches and writing, that the townes reuolted from the obedience of his Maieſtie, doe neuertheles behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues like good ſubiectes to their prynce and Soueraigne. Wherefore you muſte bringe ſomme other newes to that affect, that you &amp; I taulked of, or otherwiſe I feare, that we ſhall doe no good in this matter. I know very well your capacitye to bee ſufficient to perſwade any reaſonable matter. I know likewiſe what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1223:31"/>youe are able too doe (if youe liſt to ymploy your ſelf,) conſidering what credit you be of with all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſide. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber your promiſ: by following the which, you may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to that which I aſſured you of. For my parte I will procure you all the meanes I may, to thend that all thinges may end well. Thus lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for this tyme I pray vnto God, to geue vnto you a long and happy lief with helth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Montfort</hi> 
                  <date>this 21, of Iuly. 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Entirely your very good frende <hi>I. Perrenot.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. de Carmes</hi> and <hi>M. Iunius</hi> be in helthe</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div n="E" type="supplication">
            <head>E. A Supplication to the Kinge</head>
            <p>In most humble wyſe doo all the Knightes and Townes of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test that at all times and places they haue yelded bothe vnto your Maieſtie, and to your Predeceſſours all humble obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1223:31"/>reuerence and ſeruice, whenſoeuer it hath bin required for the maintenaunce of the greatnes, glory and Maieſty of your highnes, as became good, and faithful vaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and ſubiects to doo: in respect whereof they nothing doubte but that your Maiesties affection is increaſed thereby, the rather to conſerue &amp; mayntaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all their rights and liberties, with all quietnes and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, vnder ſounde Iustice and good pollicy. Now whereas the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> being then Gouernour for your Maieſtie ought by good reaſon to haue ſhewed himſelfe conformable to all things before ſayd: Yet hath he cleane contrariwyſe vnder the title of his gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, committed ſuch iniuries and violences vppon your countries and ſubiectes, as well ſpirituall as temporall, as well noble as not no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; as that your poore ſubiectes for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and keepinge of their priuiledges, rightes, aunciente customes, and allowed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, haue bin forced againſte theyr will to withſtande with force and armes, the proude and violente kinde of gouernmente of the ſaid Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> and his adheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſtraungers. VVho haue ſoughte
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1223:32"/>by all meanes to hinder the quietnes of your common weale, by rayſinge vp pernicious ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welties, vnwonted exactions, and generall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of your Maieſties ſubiectes. We ſee they ſhoote at noone other marke, but onely to ſubdue thinhabitants of your Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try to their appetits, and inſolencies, onely to impoueriſhe them, and bring them to bondage to the great hinderaunce of your Maieſties ſeruice, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and dominion. Whereof your ſaide oratours haue already moſte openly made ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite and proteſtacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euen as other eſtates and proui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſued for the ſame reſpect. This notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, the ſaid Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> perſiſteth and continueth ſtill in his wicked determinacion, whereby not onely the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries of your Maieſties, and thinha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitours therof are brought into great altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, calamities &amp; troubles of warre: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the kingdomes, countries and nacions ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning, haue conceiued a maruelous hatred &amp; horrour of the diſdainefull pride of theſe ſtraungers and ill willers, enemies to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon quiet, for that by them they finde both loſſe, and laying a ſide of all trafique and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicrafts, of all marchauntes trade, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1223:32"/>
            <p>Nowe therefore, ſeing that your poore Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours haue not hitherto ſought, neither do at this preſent ſeeke for any other thing, than to procure as much as they may, thaduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of their Country cauſe, for the better ſeruice of your Maieſtie, as becommeth loyall ſubiects to do: They moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly request with all reuerence, that it would pleaſe your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie like a most gentle father, to behold &amp; loke vppon the miſerable and pitifull Estate preſente of theſe Lowe Countryes, and to ſet them againe in ſome good vnity, trade, and tranquillity. Whereby both the greatnes of your Maieſtie may maruelouſly encreaſe, and alſo the prosperity of oure countrymen grow and floriſh in your ſeruice. And ſurely this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be brought to paſſe, ſo long as theſe ſtraungers ſhalbe ſuffred to vſe, and exerciſe their tyrannical gouernment, in our country: Conſidering, that all their gaines, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, conſisteth more in diſquietnes &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, than in any good order or rule. And ſurely by daily experience wee finde, that they by nature are rather giuen to their owne gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die gaine and appetites, than to ſeeke for any good to theſe Countryes, where they be but mere ſtraungers. And this is th'occaſion of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1223:33"/>our troubles and preſente warre. May it therefore pleaſe your Maieſtie, to cauſe theſe ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers to be drawen away from hence, and by fre communication and aduiſe of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Eſtates of this Country being generally and lawfully called together, to ſet and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh ſome ſuch good order pollicie and rule, as the ſaide Countries and ſubiectes of your Maiesties, may from henceforth be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mainteyned in one vnity and aſſured tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, and voyde of all troubles and inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that are to come hereafter. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, conſideringe that at the length by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuaunce of theſe preſent warres, nought els can be hoped for, than the pillinge, diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vtter destruction of your Maieſties Countryes on euery ſide: and ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that wee ſee thinhabitaunts therof to giue themſelues euery day more and more vnto th'exerciſe and feates of armes, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting quite, and laying aſide their wonted tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique and trade of Marchaundize: And ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it is, that men by nature are moſt commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enclined to all kinde of licentious libertie that warre bringeth with it, in ſuch ſort, that by longe vſe, and practize of the broyles in warre, ſuch rigour and hatred will encreaſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1223:33"/>daily amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge your Maieſt. ſubiects one agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt another, as that it is to be feared, leaſt all tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, trafiques, Marchaundizes and ſaylinges will be cleane left of to the great hinderance of your Maieſties ſeruice: The ſaide ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours do moſt humbly craue, that it will pleaſe your Maieſtie to haue regard thereunto with all clemency: ſo much the rather, for that all other prouinces and Countries adioyning, &amp; bordering, being by your Maieſties auctority diſcharged from the combenſome multitude of all ſtraung ſouldiars, may preſently by your good prouiſion, lay aſide all armes, &amp; ſurceſſe from all enmitie; ſo as the meeting and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this country may be reſtored againe with all ſurety: And that being reconciled th'one to thother, they may enioy with quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes their auncient poſſeſſions, &amp; patrimonies, by the obtayning whereof, the ſaide Oratours will not faile to performe on their partes all the duties of good and faithfull ſubiectes to your Maieſtie &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="F" type="letter">
            <head>To Mounſire M. Iunius Atauere.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Iunius</hi> I did not a whit miſcaste my accompte, when as at oure laſte beings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1223:34"/>together in the preſence of your ſelf, and <hi>M. de Carmes,</hi> I did declare vnto <hi>Monſire de Monte Saint Aldegonde,</hi> that I feared greatly leſt the writing which he brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rotterdam</hi> would find but litle fauour in the Court. For from the time that I first arriued there vntill this houre, hauing tried in euery corner how it might be taken, I finde that the opinions of all men here do ſo farre differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſiers of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there, as I dare not deale any further therein: and therefore I thought it best, to ſende you this letter together wyth the ſelfeſame request, that <hi>M. de Mont S. Aldegond</hi> brought vnto me annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, to whom I would not write, for that he may receiue no papers without peruſing, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could I write into your quarters, but by the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions. As I haue declared vnto you before this time: ſo do I thincke at this preſent, that ſom other forme of writing had bin more fit for all parts. For albeit that that which he brought was in the maner of a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, (as in deede all ſubiects ought to do towards their Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces:) Yet this which they of <hi>Holland &amp; Zeland</hi> haue offred, is to farre beſides the quallitie that ſhould be loked for in that reſpect. For firſt &amp; formoſt they would
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1223:34"/>that the king ſhould diſarme himſelf, &amp; that he ſhould not be ſerued but with ſuch as they like: not conſidering at all, that it lyeth in his power both to take or leaue armes, when hee himſelf liſteth. Who knoweth what is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for his ſubiects, and his affaires, better than himſelf? or who can tell better then he, what kinde of people will ſerue his turne best for the profit and commoditie of the ſame? Whereas in deede, it is not permitted to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, no not in a good cauſe, to take armes but by the appointment of their Lord, neither to call in any ſtraungers as thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zelande</hi> haue done: therefore their faulte is ſo much the more greuous, &amp; inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, in taking theym vppe againſt their Prince, or againſt his officers which is al one, ſince that they be ordained by him to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his perſon, &amp; to occupie his place, becauſe he himſelfe cannot be in all places at once.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as they haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded already by entering into armes of their owne priuate auctoritie, and by taking the kinges Townes, wherof, or of the reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof they make no mention at all: in very deede, in ſteede of their demaunding of that thinge at his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties hand, which they of your ſide oughte to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1223:35"/>performe if reaſon mighie take place: they ſhould truſt to the clemency of their Printe, and referre themſelues wholly thereunto. On thother ſide, it ſeemeth alſo very ſtraung, that ſubiects, wil ſeeme to inforce their Price to follow their appetite in aſſembling of Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, yea and that generally amongſt a ſorte of Seignories, which in degrees, iuriſdictions, &amp; cuſtomes haue nothing in common, but onely neighbour hode th'one with thother. In deede they haue one Lord who ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them leaue to talk at their pleaſure for their owne benefite, about their affaires, not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that this his bounty ſhoulde bee wreſted vnto any preiudice againſt himſelfe: for it ſeemeth certaine by the requeſt of this aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, that they woulde make lawes, and keepe him as Warde. Of all other pointes which I paſſe vnder ſilence, (whereof neuertheleſſe I haue oft giuen my verdite, that his Maieſty may not in any point yeld vnto) I will reherſe no more at this preſent. Of all thoſe matters, I talked at lardge with <hi>Mon. de Monte S. Aldegonde.</hi> Neuertheles the great deſire that I had to do ſome good as touchinge the quietnes of this Countrie, if God woulde permitte, and his earneſt requiringe that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1223:35"/>I woulde not lightly leaue of from this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, haue made me to do the beſt that I can, althoughe I diſpaired of any good iſſue before I began. Surely I am ſory, beſides the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſe, euen in particuler, for ſuch as I thought very well of. And for the frendſhip that I haue borne vnto the houſe of <hi>Mon. de Monte Saint Aldegond,</hi> I would haue wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that he had concluded ſomewhat more touching the affaires of <hi>Monſ. le Count de Boſſu.</hi> For after that report was made here, of the aunſwere that was made touching that matter, by <hi>M</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> vnto <hi>M. de Monte S. Aldegonde:</hi> it was deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined here, that vppon my comming it ſhould proceede no further, ſince that the good <hi>Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior de Boſſu</hi> is neuer a whit the better. I haue thoughte it good to make this reherſall vnto you of all that is paſte ſince I retourned from <hi>Mountforde,</hi> partly to let you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande of my foreward good will, and partly to aduertiſe you to ſeeke other meanes that were more expediente for the pacification of theſe your calamities. And thus I leaue, prayinge to God <hi>M. Iunius</hi> that he graunte you that which is for your health.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:1223:36"/>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Anwerpe</hi> 
                  <date>this xviij. of Auguſt. 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your frend to his power. <hi>Iohn Perrenot.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="G" type="letter">
            <head>¶ To Monſire my Lord the Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare of Aſpremont, Seigniour of S. Loup, and of Champagny. Gouernour of the Citie of Anwerpe.</head>
            <p>SIr I haue receiued not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips letter, dated the xiiij. of August, io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the request of the Eſtates, and townes of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire de Monte S. Aldegonde</hi> brought vnto you at <hi>Mountford,</hi> all the which I deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red preſently into their handes. I found that they marueyled greatelye, &amp; were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s alledged within your let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were in no pointe ſufficient, to reiect and ſend back their foreſaid requeſt after ſuch a ſort, the which peraduenture might very well haue ſerued to haue done ſome greate good. Wherefore, ſeinge themſelues to be ſo han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1223:36"/>not like ſubiectes or vaſſals of the king, as they haue alwayes ſhewed themſelues, especially where there hath bin any queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the honour, preheminence, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his Maiestie, but rather like to the greatest Infidels, Turkes or Iewer that liue in the worlde: yea and like enemies ſworne againſte his Maieſtie: they haue hereuppon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, that they are not hereafter to hope for any good at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, who ſeeke by ſuch meanes to abuſe the name of the K. to their vtter ruine, and confuſion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue agreed by Counſell, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined amongeſt themſelues, to imploye their whole power, to ſeeke oute other meanes, by which they maye better prouide for their ſurety hereafter, againſte that ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iniquitie and tyrannie of thoſe, whoe couer their owne priuate paſſions, wyth the cloake and collour of the name of the Royall Maieſtie: Proteſtinge, that ſince of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they haue no acceſſe to the eares of his Maieſtie, and are likewyſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled from that meanes which both by God and mans lawes hath bin euer graunted to the vileſt fellons, traytours, &amp; diſloyal rebels,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1223:37"/>that either are, or euer were in the worlde: ſurely they ſeele themſelues to bee forced by ſuch exceſſiue wickednes, and tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny to ſeeke for ſuch meanes as ſhall pleaſe their good God to put into their handes. Deſiring you that you wilbe a witnes to all the worlde, how that they haue preſented the foreſaid request, and thereby haue ſatiſfyed ſome part of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: And ſo maye you moſte truly excuſe and iuſtifie them, if any queſtion do ariſe hereof. And to thend that your Lordſhip may know the grounde and cauſe of their complainte, and wherefore they thincke themſelues ſo extremely iniured by the ſendinge backe of their foreſaid request: I haue thought good to gather together in forme of diſcourſe, the principall Articles of all their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint vpon your laſt letters, the which I me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue ſent you before this time, but that I wayted for your mans comming to me for my aunſweare to yours, whoe beinge come receiued his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patche without any long ſtaying. Deſiring you, wel to conſider and thinck of the reaſons and groundes alledged by them vppon your ſaid letter. I haue annexed them hereunto: but ſo neuertheles, as that this my writinge maye in no pointe be preiudiciall to the ſaide
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1223:37"/>Eſtates, and Townes, or to their reſolution. For my zeale is good, for the quiet of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, &amp; my affeclio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great to do your Lordſhip ſeruice. Well, I will remit my ſelfe vnto the diſcourſe, wherof I pray you excuſe the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and impute the fault therof either to my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abillitie, or els to the difficulty of th'affayres that are treated of therein. Thus recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my ſelfe moſt humbly &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>He that would be glad to take away the ſtoppe that hindereth me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doinge agreable ſeruice to your Lordſhip. <hi>I. Iunius de lenghe</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="H" type="discourse">
            <head>H DISCOVRSE.</head>
            <p>SIR, firſt men may thinck it ſtraunge, that the opinions of your Court ingenerall haue bin ſo farre alienated from thoſe agreements which our men did moſt deſire, that (as your letter mencioneth) you durſte not once open your mouth any further touching, that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For it is altogether vnlikely that you who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue accompted alwayes, and do accompte to be a noble gentleman, deſirous both of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1223:38"/>preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Maieſtie, and of the quiet, and tranquillitie of the common weale: haue withdrawen your ſelf from a buſines ſo much importing the ſeruice of the king, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall quiet and ſafety of the whole country: vppon the opinion of certaine priuate men, and of ſmall countenaunce in the Court. For therein you ſhould not onely do wrong to that noble minde, and valiaunte courage which I haue alwayes ſeene in you: but alſo it mighte be a diſcredite to the greate duty, and truste you owe to his Maieſtie. Wherefore, I ſaye that their opinions of whom you ſpake, haue proceeded from certaine of the priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in theſe estates, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom the king hath repoſed his chiefeſt confidence, touchinge the gouernment and rule of theſe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryes. The which Councellours, are ſworne to reueale &amp; make knowen euery thing, which in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences may any way bee preiudiciall to the kinges highnes, or commoditye. They make vs thinck aſſuredly, that you haue not conferred at all with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any ſuch matter: for if they had receiued any incklinge at all thereof, of neceſſity it muſte haue come to the kinges ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or at the leaſt to their eares who had full power and auctoritie to deale therein. Wee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1223:38"/>cannot comprehend nor imagine what ſhould ſo much coole your courage, and make you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fearde to preferre openly our requeſte, the which of neceſſitie (as you know) muſt come to their vnderſtanding. And the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that with you they doe altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne and miſlike the doinges of certaine confederate gentlemen, who preferred the like ſuite vnto <hi>Madame de Parma,</hi> in the yeare 1566. especially, becauſe that they did not rather vſe a meane more ordinary, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſome of the Eſtates, or els by ſome one principall man in the Courte, who in their names might haue exhibited their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not to haue aduaunced themſelues ſo boldly, and in ſuch maner, as they did. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandinge, by this your example you ſeeme to allow, and iuſtifie them. For you ſay, that if the Courte cannot digeſte a ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſuite, it is great folly for any one man, thoughe of auctoritie (as your ſelfe is) to take vppon him, the preferringe vppe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſuche matter, but rather by ſendinge it backe againe to incurre all daungers, which maye happen for wante of exhibitinge the ſame in conuenient time. But whereas you ſaye, that you haue not broken the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1223:39"/>matter to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but onely groped their min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des a farre of: ſurely it ſeemeth to be nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g anſwerable to that profeſſed zeale, and great affection you haue alwayes ſeemed to beare vnto the Mat. of the king, &amp; good of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. The which in my iudgemente, ſeemeth moſt manifeſt, in that you were aſerd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a requeſt ſo expedient both for the king and his countrie. Wherfore, if the euent of thinges hereafter ſhall happen to fruſtrate &amp; deceiue their opinions whoſe minds you haue but groped a farre of: aſſure yourſelfe it is impoſſible for you to eſchew ſome excedinge greate blame, in that you reiected and ſente backe without any occaſion, a requeſt of ſuch importaunce. For thoughe you ment not to follow the matter your ſelfe, yet mought you haue vttered it openly, excepte by your owne auctoritie you woulde ſeeme to depriue both King and countrie of ſo neceſſary a meanes, as to haue conſulted and determined, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the pointes of a generall pacificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreouer, if thoſe Courtiers in auctoritie and of the priuie counſell haue ſeene the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid requeſte, and would not make the Kinge acquainted therewith: yet ſhould they at the leaſt either haue publiſhed that ſelfe ſame
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1223:39"/>thing, which they wolde not communicate, or els haue geuen ſomme good aduice &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill vnto vs, withowt vſurping after that ſorte their aucthoritie, in a matter that ſo particularly did touche the Kings owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For if you reſpect but the othe only (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby his Maieſtie was ſollemly ſworne (&amp; there vpon admytted in to this countrie) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to refuſe, or reiect any Bill, or ſupplicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whatſoeuer, of any of his Subiectes, howe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane ſoeuer, and muche leſſe of corporacions and whole Prouinces: Surely you nyghte haue ſhowed a ſinguler care and earneſt deſyer for the perfourmaunce of the ſame. Moreouer, yt is altogether diſagreeing from the lawe of nature, (the which worketh effect in all people and nations) that a Prince (to whom the people haue committed their forces to thend they may be gouerned by iuſtice and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitye, and haue their cauſes harde) ſhould reiect them withowt making any care or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to vnderſtand them. This did <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> the Emperour know very well, being a Pagan and one that knew not God: who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a ſupplicacion preſented him in the ſtreetes by a poore woman, aunſwered that he had not conuenient time to looke vpon ſuche
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1223:40"/>ſmall matters: but ſhe nothing diſmayed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that if he had not leyſure to peruſe the particuler requeſtes of his poore ſubiectes, he ſhoud haue farre leſſe leyſuer to rule &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde: her reaſon was becauſ yt was the duty of a King to dooe Iuſtice. With which aunſwere he feeling himſelf touched to the quick, forth with acknowledged his fault, and afterwards peruſing her requeſt, gaue her preſently her righte. By theis we are tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arne in how great faulte they ar, which make the King culpable bothe before God and the worlde, in taking away from him the meanes to heare and vnderſtand the requeſtes of his ſubiectes, yea &amp; of his townes and whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces. The which is not only diſagreeing from the naturall care of Princes to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes: but alſo againſt the profeſſion of a Chriſtian, yea and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the particuler othewhich he is ſworne vnto. And ſure in theis reſpects owr Prince is more heauely charged, and hathe more to aunſwere for, than had that Emperour <hi>Adrian.</hi> But ſince you alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dge ſome apparaunce of reaſons, whereby it ſemeth we ought many wiſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this Preſent quarel to the arbitriment of the Prince: I beſeeche you conſider of what
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1223:40"/>force your perſwaſions may bee with them of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland.</hi> Marke whether they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be made to beleeue the contrarye, but that by theis meanes they haue been moſte yniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſtye dealt withal, and the Maieſtie of their Prince the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> moſte extremely abuſed and ſet at nought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay, they vvould that the King ſhoudle diſarme him ſelf.</hi> Surely if it weare ſoe: Yet might they aunſwere, that ſo long as the King did holde the ſworde in his hand, redy to murther them at his pleaſure, yt were great folly, (but more daunger) for them to humble them ſelues, and to ſhew that dutye which ought to be in ſubiectes to their Prince. For what could miniſter a greater likelyhod to haue all their throtes to be cutt by creditt, than this? For if he bee not armed againſt them, they will neuer wiſhe him to laye aſyde his weapens. And contrarywiſe, if hee bee, it followeth that hee becommeth, not as their King (that is to ſay, as their father and pastour,) but (which is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for him) their vtter enemye and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troyer.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:1223:41"/>
            <p>But God forbid, that thoſe good Subiectes of <hi>Holland</hi> &amp; <hi>Zeland</hi> which haue alwaies borne an eſpeciall dutie and honour to their prince, &amp; likewiſe haue fownde in him a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler kinde of clemencie towardes them, ſhoulde bee conſtrained to thinck that their king is in armes againſt them, and ſo bent to their ruine and deſtruction, as that he will not giue eare or harken to their complaintes. Nay, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne rather that certen ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſuche as are not knowen to the King, neither allied by blood nor affinitie, nor that once can cary good meaning to theis low countries, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me in the Kings name, armed at all pointes to exerciſe barbarous and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Tyrannies of their owne aucthorities: nothing eſteming the ſolemne othe &amp; firme compoſicion which the King had made, but haue brought in with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a new world, aſwell contrarye to the auncient pollecie &amp; cuſtome of lawes &amp; priuileges, As alſo againſt the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritye of the Kings Maieſtratie and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whom they pray with all humilitie, that yt woolde pleaſe him by his aucthoritye, to cauſe them to lay aſide their weapons, and to retire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, leauing the country to that gouernment which was vſed before tyme, of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1223:41"/>long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewaunce, by the prediceſſours of the Kings Maieſtie: of glorious memorye. The which if it were brought to paſſe, there ſhould be no ſubiectes more dutifull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> none more redy to acknowledge the aucthoritie of the Prince ouer them, nor none more ioifull to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhe what ſoeuer ſhoulde be commaunded them. And I pray you, how coulde you lay (I will not ſay any foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of peace) but only ſome fained apparance of an agreement, except that theis as ringleaders doe firſt geue vp their weapens and get them packing owt of this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie? vnleſſe you thinck that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to attaine to peace, dothe conſiſt in ſetting ſtraungers (yea &amp; ſtraungers of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Subiectes goods (moueables, &amp; ymmoueables,) &amp; to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vyolate their wynes and children: and that for a full end of ſuch their benifites and fauours, the ſubiects mighte doe well to interteme &amp; cheriſh them to cut al their throtes, ſo as they might at once plead full poſſeſſion, and the King be ryd of his trew ſubiects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But you ſay, that they demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that the Kinge ſhoulde not be ſerued of any, but of ſuche as they themſelues vvoulde appoint him.</hi> It ſhall neuer bee founde, that euer they did ſo muche as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1223:42"/>ymagine, that the Ki. might not make warre againſt his enemies, whoſoeuer or of what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion ſoeuer they weare, with ſuche and ſo many as he thought good, and that they be not ſo euill aduiſed as to preſcribe any lawes to his Ma. eſpecially in a thing ſovnreaſonable. But they hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeeche his Ma. that Strau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers be not lycenſed, (only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuate quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels) to make warre againſt the countrie, and townes of the King &amp; his ſubiectes: And that Spaniardes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Swiſſers, &amp; an infinite nomber of others, miht not deuide amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the booties, and ſpoiles gotten within his Ma. dominions, or at leaſt that their goodes, their wyues, and children, be not made praies nor ſubiectes to the thraldomme of ſo barbarous, and vnknowen people in theis partes. The which ſuyte, can not be conſtrued anywaies that the King ſhold altogether lay a ſide wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens. For if at any tyme his Ma. woulde make warres in theis partes or in any other, he might be hable to leauy as great an army of <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> &amp; <hi>Zeland</hi> &amp; theis Countries on horſe backe or on foote, by ſea or by lande, as eaſely ſhould be hable to reſiſt, or rather ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me his grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt enemyes, as yt hathe been appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſeene by the Predeceſſours of the Kings Mateſtie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1223:42"/>the dukes of <hi>Burgo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy,</hi> &amp; Lordes of this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie. Whoe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had no ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers neither <hi>Spa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iardes,</hi> nor <hi>Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> yet weare neuer deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titute of ſuche ſouldiars, as were ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie. But on thother ſide Duke <hi>Charles</hi> the hardy, as long as he did put his truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in theis cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triemen &amp; thinhabitantes of theis partes, &amp; gaue no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to any but <hi>Burgonio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> &amp; <hi>VVal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons:</hi> he proſpered allwayes &amp; had the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, in ſo muche as he was feared of all his neighbours. But after he begane to geue credit to ſtraungers, &amp; woulde be ſerued of <hi>Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> &amp; ſuch like which were vnder the charge of one called <hi>Campobaſſo,</hi> the caſe was altered anon after. For by the treaſon of this foreſaid <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pobaſſo</hi> (corrupted either by money, or by ſomother meanes) the Duke hauing receiued the woorſe at two battailes, at the third being before <hi>Nancy</hi> loſt bothe his lief, &amp; al the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor which his faithful Subiectes of thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries had gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before. Not with ſtanding if it be not lawfull to intreat the King not too bee ſerued in theis warres of any but theis cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen his Subiectes: Why then haue the Eſtates generally deſired the ſame of the <hi>Commandador</hi> at <hi>Bruxels?</hi> or why hathe their ſute ben accepted, ſynce yt bare all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1223:43"/>one ſhow of Rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the Kinge? For as concerning this, where you ſay, it is lawfull for the Kinge to be at warres or at peace with whome or when he liſteth: Surely you accuſe in this the Aunceſtours of his Maieſtie, who haue alwayes vowed and ſworn to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, not to make warre or to take any quarrell in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, withowt their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſentes. A thing which hath been obſerued amongeſt Princes ſynce the worlde was a worlde, and by all ſuche as woulde not publikely be eſtemed as Tyrans. For ſeeing that not only the expences of the warre, but alſo all thinconueniences, dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and miſchaunces of the ſame do fal prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally vppon the neckes of the people: ſurely both naturall reaſon, &amp; equity requyres, that ſome in their behalfe (as the Maieſtrate in ſome place, in other places the Eſtates, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes, aſſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Princes) ſhould be admitted to ſpeake &amp; ſit in cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile for their be hoofe. Except they had rather follow <hi>Xerxes:</hi> who after he had aſſembled his Counſaile of Estates, and all the Princes and Maiestrates of <hi>Perſia</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the warres he toke in hand againſt the <hi>Gretians:</hi> proteſted to them, that the chiefeſt and onely cauſe why he ſent for them, was not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1223:43"/>to thend they ſhould geue him any aduice, or counſell: but that they might heare and allow of his deuice and enterpriſe which he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready determyned and reſolued on. Where vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he was not only accompted a Tyrant, but fell into moſte opprobrious and deteſtable in famye, which continewed, to the loſſe all moſte of all his dominion. But for all this, here is nothing ſpoken to appoint the King what war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or with whome he ſhoulde wage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For let him but only ſay the woorde, when or with whome, and he ſhall fynde bothe <hi>Hollanders</hi> &amp; <hi>Zelanders</hi> in ſuche redynes, as if the dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do but ſounde, their bodies &amp; their goodes ſhalbe ſufficient pledges to ſhew their willing mindes, &amp; trew hartes they beare to their Prince, the which their prediceſſours before them haue allwayes ſhowed to the King, &amp; his aunceſtors. But here is warre made againſt the Kings owne countries, to ouerrunne the prouinces of his owne demaynes, to pil, to ſack to put to Ruin and deſtruction, his owne Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biectes. And to be ſhorte, he maketh warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him ſelf. A Prince withowt his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes is no Pince. Wherefore I meruaile you doe ſo muche miſlike that theis poor moleſted people ſhulde humbly beſeache his Maieſtie,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1223:44"/>that by his aucthoritye and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, this warre ſo hurt full to them, ſo vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the King, ſo deteſtable before God, and ſo to be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and pitied of all honeſt min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, might ceaſſe. <hi>You ſay the King knovves vvhat his ſubiectes haue neede of.</hi> Would youe by this maintayn that it is conueniente that the Kings Subiectes ſhoulde be robbed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doone, and murdred by ſtraungers, their how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes burnt, their townes ſpoilled, their feelds wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, their inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces decaied, their wyues &amp; daughters deſlowred, and their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> led vnder the ſeruitude of Strau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers? The which if it bee conuenyent and neceſſarye for the Kings Subiectes: ſurely it were better for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vnder the protection of the moſte cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Tiraunt that euer reigned. Except (as in deed yt appeareth) the King hath not ſoe commaunded, ſynce he vnderſtandes ſo well what is moſte conuenyent for his Subiectes. Therefore haue they great reaſon, with all humillity to referre them ſelues to his moſte gracious order, commaunding all forreigners too gett them packing owt of the countrie. But if you ſay the woorſt you can, and think to cut all their throotes by a worde ſpeaking, in ſaying theis men are rebels to the King, &amp;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1223:44"/>therefore cannot be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted as his ſubiects: Leauing to debate this queſtion preſently, which woulde be bothe long and tedious, they wil only aunſwere you thus. That if they bee rebels, you ought to leaue that to the Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his Maieſtie, vnto whome they ſubmitted them ſelues by their foreſaid requeſt, &amp; that you ought not (by ſending the ſame backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine) to take away from his Ma. al his righte of equitie, &amp; Iuſtice, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the meanes they had for their iuſtification. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that which you take for a Maxime <hi>That it is not lavvful for any ſubiecte to take armes in handes, vvithout thorder and appointment of their Lordes:</hi> It will appeare to al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, that it is ſuche a kinde of ſpeache, as can haue no good ground of truthe, becauſe yt is ſo generall. For if the Lorde be owt of the countrie, and the ſaid countrie be ſodenly in vaded by enemyes, I doe not thinck that your meaning is in this caſe by this your lawe, that men ſhoulde make adoubt of taking weapens in hand, vntill their countrie weare clene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerrunne &amp; ſpoilled. For by that meanes you muſt condemne the Dukes of <hi>Burgo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy</hi> the Prediceſſore of his Maieſtie, of fellony and treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that they being then the vaſſals of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1223:45"/>the King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> yea (and that more is) lincked very nere vnto him in ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of blood, and hauing yelded vnto him their homage &amp; fealtye, did take armes, not only withowt his appointment, but alſo againſt his owne perſon and eſtates in the feeld. Surely no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make me beleue, but that the good Duke <hi>Phillip</hi> knew very well, what was the dutye of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as (to reuenge the deathe of Duke <hi>Ihon</hi> his father, who alitle before had ſlayne the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> brother to the King (he cauſed the King of <hi>England</hi> to comme into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and made him Lorde of the Cittye of <hi>Paris,</hi> and of the beſt parte of the whole kingdome. If this lawe which nou ſet downe here, were ſo generall as you woulde make it ſurely he had neuer atteined vnto the name of ſo good a Prince as he was accompted, neither had he lefte behinde him to his poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erity ſo good a reporte of immortall glory as wee know of. Likewiſe his ſonne <hi>Charles</hi> the hardy, when he tooke armes againſt <hi>Lois</hi> the. 11. and defeated a parte of his armye at <hi>Monthelery:</hi> knew not hee very well that ſubiectes mighte make no ſturre withowt appointment or aucthoritie from their Lorde? wil you ſay then that owr King doothe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1223:45"/>wrongfully enioy the countye of <hi>Burgondy,</hi> the which was graunted by the ſame <hi>Lois</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> vnder the title that the ſubiect did beare armes againſt his liege Lorde? But howe often hathe it been ſene, and iudged to be right and reaſonable, that the ſubiectes in particuler, and the Townes and Prouinces in generall haue taken Armes in ſuch caſes as this, not only withowt the appointment of their Lorde, but alſo euen againſt their ſoueraignes them ſelues, and yet hathe nether your lawe nor Maxime been of ſufficient waight againſt the reaſons, and argumentes that they alledged in defence of their equytie. Wherefore of force your concluſion cannot holde, when as you inferre by this your Maxime, that they of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> haue committed an offence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, in hauing taken armes againſt their Prince. For firſt you ſhoulde haue declared that the groundes, and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that forſte them therevnto were not reaſonable, or at the leaſt not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to maynteyne the equitye of their cauſe: and then mighte you haue had ſomme bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of reaſon. But ſurely it ſeemeth, that for becauſ you wolde haue the equitye of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1223:46"/>their cauſe quyte ſuppreſſed from the eares of the worlde, and from the knowledg of his Maieſtie, you haue cleane troden vnder foote and ſent backe againe their requeſt: grownding your ſelf only vpon the opinions of ſuche of the courte, as you knewe before to bee aduerſaries to their attemptes. And I pray you, what if theis of owr ſide ſhall ſay, that they not only haue not taken ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes againſt his Maieſtie, but alſo that they haue not ſtirred, but by his conſent and aucthoritie? Dothe it not ſeeme vnto you rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that the othe (which the King hath taken, and the expreſſe article wherin he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth that no man ſhall any longer yelde obedience vnto him ſelf, than he obſerueth the points of the artiles that he is ſworne vnto) may iuſtifye their doinges, eſpecially ſeeing that bothe his Maieſtie is abſent, &amp; that ſtraungers, vnder the title of his name, haue not only broken theis articles, but alſo ſoughte vtterli to diſanull that ſollemne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, the which he made at his entrye into <hi>Brabant,</hi> which is the chiefeſt of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces he poſſeſſeth in theis partes? for as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that which you ſaie, <hi>That to beare armes againſt his Maieſtie or his Miniſters is all one:</hi> I cannot comprehend, where of that ſhould be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1223:46"/>grounded, conſidering that the King him ſelf at his foreſaid entry and acceptacion, dothe promiſe, ſweare, &amp; declare, that preſently &amp; <hi>ipſo facto</hi> all officers, Maieſtrates ad My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſhalbe taken but for ſciphers, &amp; of no validity, who either haue ben heere before, or ſhalbe hereafter placed in preiudice of thoſe articles, which he is ſworne vnto, or that ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any thing againſt the ſame. So that the King him ſelf dothe by his othe diſgrade all ſuche miniſters, and dothe put weapens into owr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to reſiſt their iniquitye &amp; viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And if that you graunte that all this is trew, in reſpect of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Brabant,</hi> but that <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> may be no partakers thereof: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſte you needes Iuſtifie the Prince of <hi>Ore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,</hi> and all thoſe that ſerue him, being bothe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes &amp; naturally borne in <hi>Brabant,</hi> in that they wolde not acknowledge ſuche miniſters, as haue violated and broken the othes and contractes of the King. And ſince that they wear not bounde to acknowledge or allow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but mighte take armes againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it followeth that they might with good reaſo occupie &amp; enioy all thoſe landes &amp; Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which did yelde any fauour, or deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon at any tyme to ſuche myniſters, being
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1223:47"/>diſanulled and diſgraded. And as touching the reſt of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> their fault and offence can be none other, but that they bee not borne in <hi>Brabant.</hi> For I cannot thinck that you wil denie, but that the ſaid miniſters againſt whome they beare armes, haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and violated in a maner all thoſe articles which the King was ſworne vnto at his firſte entrye. And if thies things were not thus: what is he that ſeeth not plainly, how that in this point the Kings hands be faſt tyed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſynce that your ſelues doe confeſſe, that in all matters Eccleſiaſticall and touching faithe, he is bounde to be obedient vnto the Pope, his legates, and vicars. Dooe not we know how that, that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded vpon, and ordeined amongeſt your eccleſiaſtical perſons, and Biſhops, to roote owt this owr religion, which you call new, was inuented and forged by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, being ſollicited therevnto by Docter <hi>So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nius</hi> who for that cauſe remayned at <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> by the ſpace of three or fower yeares, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde broughte amongeſt vs into theis quarters the peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeed of theis troubles, &amp; calamities, that we feele at this day? Do not we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1223:47"/>knowe that it was onely the Pope, which gaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the king, that thordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> ſhould be publiſhed here, againſte the which all the Estates both Eccleſiasticall and Temporall did ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to withstand, as a thing preiudiciall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aunciente lawes, cuſtomes and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges which the king hath ſworn vnto vs? Briefly, haue not all the Instruments and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of this Tragedy bin created onely by the Pope? And who is ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I pray you, that the Pope in his decres doth openly vaunte that all kinges and Princes are bound to hold all their Crownes and Scepters of him, and to obey him in euery point? Haue we no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of our aunceſtours, how that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opes of <hi>Rome</hi> haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded at their plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, the most noble Emperours and Prince<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and ſought to execute their wils by excommunicating and accurſinge of them, as often as they would reſiſt their pleaſures? Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence proceeded thoſe cruell and bloudy warres betweene the three <hi>Henries, Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> and an inſinite nomber of other Emperours agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the Popes of <hi>Rome:</hi> but for becauſe that the ſame Emperours, woulde not obey their Commaundementes,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1223:48"/>ſometimes when they willed them to make warre in all haſt vppon the <hi>Sarraſins,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when they woulde haue them leaue of that title which they had receiued by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of their aunceſtours, ſometimes when the Popes themſelues would be put in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of certaine townes and territories, which they ſaid, they ſhould inherite as the patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and finally vppon any cauſe that it pleaſed them to picke, whereof all the Chronicles and Hiſtories be filled. And what was the cauſe why Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> marched in publique place vppon the necke of the Emperour <hi>Fredericke Barbaroſſa,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto many wordes full of reproche and ſhame? And what is the cauſe againe, why euen at this day they make the Monarks and kinges to kiſſe their feete, but onely in ſigne and token of ſubiection which they claime as due? And preſently if they be not obeyed, they thunder againſte them: and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce abſolution vnto all their ſubiectes, although they reuolt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fidelitie which they owe of duty. Wherfore ſeing that the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is ſo much ſubiect to the Pope of Rome (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no wiſe we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acknowledge to be our ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour) &amp; ſince <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> he feareth ſo much his thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings &amp; exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications: How can you ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1223:48"/>ſay or beleue, that his Ma. doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abſolutely amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gst vs what he liſteth himſelf, ſpecially in ſuch a matter wherin <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Pope pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to haue more interreſt than any man aliue? I beſeech you if the king woulde here our requeſts, &amp; finding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grounded vppon good reaſons, were willing to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: do you thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ck that it were lawfull for him ſo to do? Your ſelfe haue tould me very plainly, <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> if the king would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to any ſuch matter, you would take armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt him, &amp; cauſe (to your power) the whole cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie to rebell. And this I am ſure your ſelf wil not denie to haue ſaid, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was with you at <hi>Mountford.</hi> Wher the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remayneth the fre auctoritie of the king to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund? where is <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> greatnes of his Ma. yea rather what becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of his liberty &amp; of your Maxime, that no ſubiecte may take armes in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d without <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his king &amp; lord, ſeing that one only vaſſal wil to his power cauſe al his Eſtats to rebell, if that the aduice &amp; opinion of his Maieſty, touching the cauſe of his Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try &amp; ſubiects, ſhal not agre with his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite? But I am contente to pardon you herein, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the zeale which you beare to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe Religion, vppon condition that you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1223:49"/>will imagine that oure zeale which we beare vnto our Apoſtolicall Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpel, is not a whit leſſe, althoughe peraduenture it is nether ſo plauſible in mans capacitie, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo profitable to them that maintaine it. Yet haue we examples very freſhe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Charles</hi> of noble memorie, who eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped very hardly from beinge excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Pope <hi>Paulus 3.</hi> for that hee graunted vnto the Almaynes but onely the <hi>Interim,</hi> which was almoſt conformable in all poincts vnto the decrees of the Pope. And I pray you what ado was there when he willed that a generall Councell ſhoulde be called in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, where the Almaynes might be harde in free disputacion? And finally was it not the Pope, that conſtrained him to make warre vpon the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and did oftentimes threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him with thundringes, if he wente not to worke with ſpeede, in ſuch ſort that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was conſtrayned to couer the pretence of his warre with the cloke of rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he might draw vnto him <hi>Mawrice</hi> and th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes which were confederates of the <hi>Smalcaldiens?</hi> I ſpeake nothing here of the holy Inquiſition of Spaine, nor of the Prelates of the Counſayle, which be of the Popes crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1223:49"/>and haue made a ſolempne othe vnto him, neuer to agree to anye matter that they ſhall thinck to be preiudicial to the aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> but that they ſhall reueale the ſame, and reſist it with all their power. Who ſeeth not how that our king is ſo poſſeſſed with them, as hee is not able by anye meanes in the world, to iudge any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in this matter contrary to their opinions &amp; aduice, vppon paine of being condempned for a rebel vnto the ſea of <hi>Rome?</hi> Howe then can that be true where you ſay, that wee make warre vppon the king? Take away once the respect of the Pope and his Prelates, and bringe to paſſe that either the king himſelf be not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte vnto him or els that he be content that we may be free from his lawes: and then ſhall you ſee how ſoone and how ſoundlye, wee will yeld our ſelues vnto the perfect obedience of our king &amp; naturall Prince, as to one annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God himſelf to do vs right &amp; Iuſtice? And if you esteeme this to be vtterly vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and that you meane to make the minde of oure Prince to be at the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente of other mennes willes: do not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile I pray you, if we pretend to be no rebels in ſeeking that he maye gouerne vs by his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1223:50"/>Auctoritie, withoute receyuing lawes from others. I come now to that other poinct where you ſay, <hi>That it is a very ſtraung thing for ſubiectes to force their Prince to aſſemble Eſtats at their pleaſure.</hi> Surely this ſeemeth very wonderfull, conſidering that you cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how that the king himſelf by his owne pure will, hath tyed himſelfe thereunto, as to the firmeſt ground and ſureſt ſtaffe whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, his auctority &amp; power Regall doth chiefly (yea I may ſay, onely) leane &amp; reſt. For ſeing the Eſtates in a fourme of politique gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are none other thing but the chiefe and principall heads of the people repreſenting the body of the multitude: What thing is there, that can bee ſo naturally vnited vnto a good king, who deſireth to be both father and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour of his people, as are the Eſtates of his Country? Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, there is nothing that hath ſuch affinity with the head of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bodye, as thoſe members which are called vital, for that they be the chiefest Inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts by the which the vitall ſpirits proceding from the braynes to diuers ſinewes, are communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in generall to the whole body, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery member, and by the which likewyſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery member retayneth his perfecte vnity,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1223:50"/>and naturall knitting to the body. Euen ſo a good king, being the head of his people, doth by the meanes of his Eſtates, communicate and imparte vnto the whole body of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, not onely his fauoure, grace &amp; priuiledges, whereby he keepeth them in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: but alſo his bounty, Iustice and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, from the which as out of a quicke foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, do ſpringe good lawes &amp; Ordinaunces, whereby the people are ſtill gouerned in good diſcipline, as it were in the liuely being and naturall motion of the ſame. This is the cauſe why our auncestours excelling in wiſedome and perfecte pollioy, haue very well ordeyned heretofore, that especially the king ſhould ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtraightly be bounde and vnited with the Estates of the Country, not to do any thing of importau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce without communicating the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto them firſte, as they on the other ſide oughte to behaue themſelues vnto theyr Prince, as to their heade giuen to theim of GOD. From hence is proceeded the great and vniforme loue and Fidelitie, which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in theſe partes haue borne to their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they likewiſe to them. And ſurely this principle appeared in the perſon of the good Duke <hi>PHILIP,</hi> who at the firste
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1223:51"/>vnited all thoſe low Countries into one body, and made many lawes, the aſſured vnitye which either is or oughte to bee betweene a Prince and his people. Eſteeminge it better to be beloued &amp; called father by them, than to be feared and redouted of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For he knew well ynoughe, that loue is the ſureſt grounde and faithfulleſt garde of all gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, in ſuch ſort, that they be great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be deteſted, and to be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted publique peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, who to bringe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in credite by villanies and ſeruile flatteries, vnder the pretence of maintayning the auctoritie of our Prince, haue whispered in the eares of his councell, that whoſoeuer talketh of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſemble of the Eſtates, doth catch at the Crowne from his Maieſties head. For ſurely theſe be the auctours of all tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nies, troubles, and inſolencies: theſe be the diſturbers of our common quiet: theſe be the enemies both of God and the worlde, although they attribute neuer ſo much wiſdome and experience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues: doing in this caſe not vnlike vnto him that would diſmember the parts of the body from the head, and depriue them of their vertues and naturall actions, vnder the pretence of doing good to the head. True it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1223:51"/>is, that for a time they ſeeme to yelde as it were a ſtaye and proppe vnto the power of Princes in cauſinge theym in generall to be more feared than loued: but in thende they ſhew themſelues to ſeeke noughte els, but the fall of Princes, and the ouerthrow of all their people at one time: as wee ſee moſt clearely by th'example of the kingdome of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> the calamitie and ruine whereof, hath not proceded from any thing els, but by the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thordinaunces of the Eſtates generall, and by ſufferaunce that the kinge mighte go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne at his owne appetite with abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, without hauing regard either to the body politique, or to them that ſhould repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſame. I would to GOD that this poore Country of ours would behold it ſelfe in this glaſſe, which is ſo cleare &amp; ſo neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, without fallinge into the ſame inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences. But our ſinnes being already growen to a certaine rypenes, haue haſtened our vtter ouerthrowe, in blindinge the eyes of ſuch go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, as haue perſwaded our Princes to thinck, that their ruine conſiſteth in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the generall Estates of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, whoſe order is a common conſente to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue vppon ſuch pointes, as do concerne the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1223:52"/>tranquillitie of the ſame: whereas, if at the least this had bin lookt vnto in the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, before that thoſe troubles did breake out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo great a flame according to thoſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which the Gentlemen of the confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates gaue vnto his Maieſtie: ſurely then might all the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences which haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſince, haue very well bin auoyded. Yet at length let vs looke, although very late, firſt which be the grounds and occaſions that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs from hauinge recourſe vnto that ſo ready and wholſome a remedie, which in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt hath alwayes bin the refuge, both of Prince &amp; People, when any inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience did threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. You ſay <hi>That ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries do conſiſt vppon diuers Seignories, vvhich in degree, iuriſdictions and cuſtomes haue nothing to do the one vvith the other, but onely a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhode vnder one Lord: therefore they are not to compell the king to aſſemble the eſtates gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</hi> I beſeech you then ſirs, If wee ſhoulde demaunde of the kinge to aſſemble onely the Eſtates of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces haue alwayes bin ioyned together, and that by their aduiſe hee woulde ordaine ſome conuenient remedies for theſe preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles &amp; calamities, euen as his Maieſties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1223:52"/>the Princes of <hi>Bauier</hi> were wont to do in the like caſes, not adding any other to theſe Prouinces, except it were <hi>Hainault</hi> and <hi>Oſtrenant:</hi> woulde you iudge then that wee had any reaſon on oure ſides? At the leaste your argumente whereon you ſeeme to ground moste, would ſeeme to be of no force. And I ſurely do thincke that this particuler aſſembly (ſince that you cannot abyde the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) were much fitter for the people of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> than th'other weare which they demaunde. But I pray you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what wrong they of <hi>Holland</hi> &amp; <hi>Zeland</hi> haue committe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in ſubmitting themſelues in their foreſayd requeſt vnto thorder of their Prince, without preſuming to preſcribe any law vnto him, or in referringe themſelues to the Iudgement of the generall Eſtates of all the low Countries, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were content to ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to thend that they might not ſeeme to ſeeke to be iudges in their owne cauſe? And if there be no reaſon at all to aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the generall eſtates of ſo many and diuers Proui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, in a matter <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> toucheth only one par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler Prouince: then I pray you, why ſhould <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the Eſtats of <hi>Brabant</hi> &amp; <hi>Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</hi> preſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, wherin they would admit
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1223:53"/>Religion but that of <hi>Rome:</hi> bee preiudiciall vnto them of <hi>Holland and Zeland?</hi> Howe be it ſurely (if all be well conſidered) this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is growen ſo generall in all theſe prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as it cannot be remedied but by a mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine generally taken. For who knoweth not howe that in this cauſe, there are ioyned to <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zelande,</hi> in a maner all <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derland, Phriſeland,</hi> and <hi>Ouerijſel</hi> wyth many both of the townes and peoples of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Flaunders, Hainault</hi> and <hi>Arthois?</hi> who vnderstandeth not, that (when this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was preſented by thoſe gentlemen in the yeare 66. there were almost as many of oure Prouince, as of any other, yea and that the nomber of them of <hi>Hainaulte, Arthois</hi> and <hi>Nanin</hi> did farre exceede them of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zelande?</hi> Wherefore if ſome haue bin frighted by force and threatninges, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppreſſed by the tyranny of the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> and ſome againe haue not bin able to finde oute the oportunities and open wayes which they of <hi>Hollande</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> haue founde: is it therefore to be ſaide that they ought to be barred from giuinge ayde and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to quench this great fier, and generall cauſe of Ruine? No: for this is certaine, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1223:53"/>the harme which proceedeth of theſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, doth touche the other Prouinces as neere as it doth <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland.</hi> For if it happen that theſe Countryes bee either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed or alienated from the obedience of the Kinge. Conſider I pray you whether <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> and <hi>Flaunders</hi> with many other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces ſhalbe ſubiect to any inuaſion that firſt will aſſaulte them or not, and how in ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, hauinge loſte the commoditie of the Sea, they may be releaued with vitaile, or ſuccoured from <hi>Spaine</hi> or <hi>Italie?</hi> In ſo much that to barre alother Prouinces from this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie, is nought els than to ſeeke the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to depriue the Kinge and his ſucceſſours from all poſſeſſion of any eſtate or Prouince in theſe parts. But let vs ſee how theſe matters will hang together. You ſay, <hi>That it is but by ſpeciall grace and fauour, that the aunceſtoure of our king haue ſuffered and permitted a generall Conuocation of the Eſtates in vrgente affayres.</hi> Admit that it were ſo: yet ſurely it were a great diſcurteſie to perſwade the king to ſhew leſſe fauour vnto theſe Countries than his predeceſſours haue done: and it were the waye to force him to ſeeke ſome other kinde of ſuperioritie, and gouernemente, cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1223:54"/>to that which they followed, in ſuch ſort that thereof nought els can be hoped for, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a contrary fruit to that which they gathered, that is to ſay, the hatred of ſubiects in ſteede of loue, and tyranny in place of good gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and finally vtter deſtruction in ſteede of flouriſhing prosperitie. But ſure I cannot imagine that you are ſo ignorant of the Chro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicles, or ſuch a ſtraunger to the knowledge of the ſtate of theſe Countries, as that you know not how that ſince the time of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,</hi> theſe Countries and Prouinces haue euer bin vnited in one body together, with ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other neighbours &amp; borderers, vnder the title of beinge called <hi>Auſtraſia or Lorein,</hi> which toke that name, for that in diuiſion, that part fel to one of his nephews called <hi>Lho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thayre:</hi> and how that afterward by diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſucceſſours, beinge diſmembred thone from the other, yet they did alwayes keepe a certaine vnitie of Amitie and alliaunce to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, euen vntill the tyme of the good Duke <hi>Philip,</hi> who broughte them againe into one body, and tyed them faſt and vnſeperable by many good ordinaunces, lawes and priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which he gaue vnto them in generall, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing him ſelfe therein to be both a father to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1223:54"/>his Country, &amp; a paſtour to his people, in ſuch ſort that it was offred vnto him by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Pope for that tyme, to make therof a kingdome, the which he would neuer agree vnto, both becauſe that he would not offer by ſuch innouations any kinde of preiudice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Priuiledges of the Proui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes particulerly, neither yet go againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes that he had ſworne vnto them. And if you liſte to alledge, that oure Kinge doth at this preſent occupie certain prouinces which then had nothing a do with them: I will aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that likewiſe the foreſaid Duke did at that time enioy certaine others, almost of like importaunce, the which haue ſince that time bin ſeperated, and diſmembred in ſuch ſort, that the ſaid good Duke <hi>Philip</hi> being recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the poſſeſſion of <hi>Hollande</hi> and <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande</hi> almost in the ende of his raigne, did leaue this coniunction of theſe Prouinces vnto his ſonne and onely heire <hi>CHARLES</hi> the hardy, who being of a more hauty minde went about openly to make theſe Countries a kingdome, had he not bin hindered part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye by the Estates of the ſaide Countries whoe withſtoode the ſame, and partly by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1223:55"/>the diſfauour of the Emperour <hi>Frederick 3.</hi> who raigned at that time. But let the cauſe be as be may: hee left vnto his daughter and heire, the ſucceſſion of all the ſaid countries, as one body vnited and knitte together with many faſte and ſtraighte bandes: after the which ſorte <hi>Maximilian</hi> her huſbande the Emperour, and his ſonne the Archeduke <hi>Phillip,</hi> receiued the ſame, and in ſuch ſort lefte theim vnto the Emperour of noble me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory <hi>Charles</hi> the fifte father to oure Kinge: who being not content with the foreſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction and bandes, and as it were foreſeing how that afterwards ſome would go about to ſowe hatred amongſt them, and to ſet th'one againſt thother, vnder this prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that they had nothinge common amonge themſelues: tooke awaye and aboliſhed from theim all the diuerſitie of Queſtions that mighte encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, ſome from vnder the Crowne of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> ſome from the title of the Empyre, and ſome from other places. And at a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall diet of Almaigne, by the conſente of all the Electours and Eſtates of the Empyre, hee vnited and broughte together all theſe prouinces into one compaſſe or Circle of the Empyre, ordayning and appointing that from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1223:55"/>that tyme forward, all they ſhould ioyntly and vnſeperably be acknowledged too be of the Empire, and that for that cauſe, they ſhoulde pay in thordinary contribucions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as muche as twoe Electors did. And this hath been inuiolablye kept bothe of his Maieſtie: of noble memory, And alſo by own king and Maiſtar that now is, ſo farre foorth as that his Maieſtie did ſende one <hi>S.</hi> of <hi>Hoochſtrate</hi> into <hi>Almaigne</hi> in his name, to acknowledge the foreſaid prouinces as one bodye politique ioyned to the Empire. And for ſuch were they taken at that time: ſoe that I cannot ſufficienly meruaile, howe you can ſaye that in degrees and Iuriſdictions they be ſo dyuers, and that there is nothing common amongſt them, but only neighborhod. And I pray you how hapneth yt then, that in all Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribucions and reliefs, they be euer aſſembled generally, and that the participacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of eache relif, is gathered according to the abillitye and facultie of euery prouince? Woulde you wiſhe that in the tyme of contributing, the prouinces ſhoul be but one bodye, and that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſeeke to remedie the euident Ruine of the whole countrie in generall, eache ſhould ſeeke for their remedye in particuler, with owt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1223:56"/>ioyning thone to thother? ſurely in my ſimple Iudgement this thing is not onlye withowt all reaſon, but alſo dothe ſimell of tooto tyrran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius wyckednes. But what ſhall we ſay? when his Maieſtie propounded the neceſſitie of his warre with <hi>Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> in the yeare 1557: in what ſorte did the Eſtates then chardg them ſelues with that great burden, but only in generall? the which warre in thend of nine yeres with a ſingle fidelitye ſhewed towardes their King, &amp; a woonderfull vnitye kept among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, they brought to happy end by their nine yeres co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tribucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the great glorye &amp; honour of his roiall Maieſtie. Is it reaſon then that in making warre vpon a ſtraunge Prince, theys prouinces ſhalbe but one body, and the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vnited together: and that in turninge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from themſelues an vtter overthrow pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cured by this ciuill warre, they ſhalbe counted diuers &amp; diſmembred, &amp; not be ſuffred to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the eſtates general, to thende that by a generall remedye they may help and cure a common maladie? But is it not plaine howe that in all thinges wherein any prouinces borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together, may by any meanes be ioyned and vnited: theis countries be and haue ben always in the ſame ſorte vnitid more than
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1223:56"/>any others? for from whence proceedeth that cuſtome which they haue euer had to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Townes and prouinces in the exercyſe of the bowe, and other armes left vnto vs by our prediceſſours, but only by this vnitye? Howe cometh it to paſſe, that at feaſtes and publique places, the townes &amp; prouinces haue bin alwayes called together by publique aucthority: but only to ſhewe the vnity of the poore countrie, euen as <hi>Grece</hi> did by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblye at their <hi>Olimpiades?</hi> Is not the name of the Baſe <hi>Almaignes</hi> or <hi>Flemings</hi> (as the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> do cal vs at this day) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnto vs all? The ſpeache althoughe it be diſtinctly of diuers ſortes, yet is ſo common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, that in the ſelf ſame townes they be vſed equallye. The iuriſdictions owt of owr ſoueraigne court, doe they not almoſte gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally proceed from Machlyne? and all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall proceſſes, Doe not they of auncient cuſtome proceed eyther from <hi>Coleigne</hi> or from <hi>Maians?</hi> What ſhoulde I ſay more, than that owr whole countre is but one Circuyte or Prouince of the Empire? Doe you then thinck yt ſo ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, that an Imperial Circuyt ſhoulde aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble eſtates iointlie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydering that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1223:57"/>ſhoulde otherwiſe ſeeme monſtruous, if one Prouince ſhould be aſſembled withowt the reſt? But paraduenture you will ſay, that this warre in the reſpect of <hi>Brabant</hi> is no Ciuill warres: the which ſayeng no man of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will affirme. And if there were none other thing to alledge, but that owr King and the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> had made al their Edicts and Plackartes of Religion in generall to all the prouinces, weare not that a ſufficient Argument to confute your ſaying, that they haue nought in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon the one with thother? yea rather is it not a full iuſtification of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of thoſe of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> in that point, if you will be ruled by right and reaſon <hi>Quod omnes attingit, ab omnibus probari debet?</hi> for if the rigowr of thoſe Placartes laid vpon all theis Prouinces in generall, hathe cauſed a generall alteracion of the people: Why ſhoulde not we aſſemble and call together the generall eſtates of theis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, to remedye ſuche inconueniences as generally doe light vpon vs all? And ſure this is the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by thoſe two cauſes that you alleadged, for the which Princes in tymes paſt were wont to aſſemble generall eſtates, that is to witt, <hi>the benefit of their Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1223:57"/>and the vveale of their affaires.</hi> For they coulde neuer be better ſpoken, of than at this preſent, when we treat not of one ſimple benifitt, but of the whole ſaffetye of owr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and eſpeciall reſtitucion of his Maieſties dignitye. Wherefore if euer there weare cauſe to aſſemble eſtates in generallitye, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now there is greater cauſe ſoe to doe than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ther was. This notwithſtanding (if I may ſpeake of myne owne hed, witheowt thaduiſe of the Eſtates and Townes in theis partes) I doe thinck that if the King or his counſell be offended with this generallity, they will be content to haue agraunt from his Maieſtie that they may lawfully aſſemble the ſtates on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> and that it will pleaſe hym to ratifie that which they ſhall find by ſounde cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell and deliberacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be fit for his Maieſties ſeruice, and for their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries ſaffetye. Conſidering that herin (as I haue ſaid) they haue had agreater reſpect to the Auctorite of the King, than to any thing els. But it ſeemeth that there is ſome other hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe which moueth you to be ſo ſuſpitious of this aſſembling of eſtates in that you ſaye <hi>that this requeſt ſeemeth to be made as it vvere to tye him to a lavv, and to kepe him as a vvarde</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1223:58"/>beleue but that this proceedeth rather of ſome ill grounded conceytes, or ſiniſter ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of ſuche in the court; as cannot diſgeſt owr ſimple peticion, than of your owne good iudgement or aduiſe. I cannot be parſwaded that you can digreſſe ſo farre from all reaſon. For ſurely you know well ynoughe, howe that the moſte true and legittimate power and dignitie of all kinges, monarches, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, &amp; the greateſt vnitye &amp; proſperitye of all people and prouinces, dothe eſpecialie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and principally depende vpon the aſſemble of eſtates: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it appeareth in <hi>Almaigne</hi> &amp; in al other Kingdomes &amp; Prouinces which are wel &amp; quietly gouerned. For thoſe aſſembles which we call Edictes in the comon wealthe, are euen the ſame which in the churce of God were called counſelles, the which owr au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, holy fathers &amp; doctors in the Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue churche helde in ſuche reuerence &amp; eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion, as that they ordeigned that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> half yere to half yeare, or at the furtheſt from yere to yere, generall Sinodes ſhould bee called as often as any neceſſitye required. Whereunto they euer had a moſte ſoueraigne recourſe, vntill ſuche tyme as that the great power of the Popes did ſubdewe the Sinodes by their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1223:58"/>abſolute aucthoritie, againſt the which owr forefathers at mani tymes, and eſpeciallye in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of <hi>Baſil,</hi> did moſte openly reſiſt. They ordeigned that from tenne yere to ten yeares a generall counſell and Synode ſhould be called thorow owt all Chriſtendome wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the Pope himſelf ſhoulde be ſubiect. Which thing was ſo odious vnto the ambicion of the ſucceſſours of that Pope, as that to their power they haue hindred euer ſince the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the councelles, ſo farr foor thas that in the great neceſſitye of Chriſtendome, and at the earneſt ſolliciting of the Emperour <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> the councell of <hi>Trent</hi> was at length cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and prolonged almoſte by the ſpace of 30. yeres after with a 1000. Kindes of delayes &amp; excuſes to delay the ſame. After that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the councell of <hi>Conſtaunce, Thoan</hi> the 32. one of the 3. Popes that were degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at that tyme, being accuſed of 50. articles at the leaſt, and all thoſe cryminall, ſighing ſore, aunſwered thus: that beſides all thoſe faultes, he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted a greater offence, &amp; that was for becauſe that he had ſuffered ſuche a free councell to be called as him ſelf was bounde to be ruled by, &amp; the reby he him ſelf was with great infamye depoſed. I doe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1223:59"/>alledge all this, to ſhowe that it is the parte of Tyrantes only to miſlike generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and that all good Princes Kinges and Emperours haue alwaies deſicred theis diet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and aſſemblies, as all good prelates haue (to their power) procured the aſſemble of Synodes and councels in the Churche of God. For this is certein, that whereas many doe aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and conſult, (whether yt be for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welthe, or of the churche of God,) there ordinarily is God him ſelf preſident, &amp; ſendeth his goodſpirit, lightninge moſte commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly the eyes of a nomber in ſuche caſes, as paraduenture one alone or a fewe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcerne awhit. Wherefore me thine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that in this caſe they of <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> &amp; <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> haue declared what great confidence they haue in the mercifull gouernment and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of the King, in hauing ſet be fore his face the true and only meane to pacifie the troubles of this countrie. For ſynce that in any wiſe they muſte make no queſtions of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what coulde they in this worlde offer with more humilite and better right, than to ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolues to the Iudgement of his Maieſtie: in a generall aſſemble of all owr eſtates, ſhewing therin that they feared not at all to haue
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1223:59"/>their cauſe brought to light before the face of the whole world and of his Maieſtie, becauſe they felte themſelues cleare from all crimes which wrongfully were laide to their charge? And if their religion were ſo wicked as the Kinge is informed that it is: what can they do more ſincerely than with humble ſute to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest that it might be iudged and tryed, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by thoſe who haue proteſted moſt plainly, that they will by no meanes admit or receiue the ſame? Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be any thing more conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c for the dignity and honour of his Maieſtie, or for to expreſſe their owne faithfull ſeruice, than to ſubmit themſelues wholly to the iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of his Ma. and of thoſe Eſtates which he ſhall lawfully call together? It ſeemeth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that you amongſt you do feare and flye from the iudgement and aduice of the kinge, and that you take him to be ſo childiſhe, as that he cannot diſcerne white from blacke, or els that your ſelues muſt preſcribe him what he ſhall do. For you hindered our requeſt from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge to his cares. It falleth out now, that your ſelues are they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> make the king a Ward, in that you will not ſuffer him to here the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and ſutes of his ſubiectes. This is to take the Crowne from his Maieſtyes head, &amp;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1223:60"/>to make your ſelues kinges: Conſidering that the dignity and prehemie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nce of Royalty, doth not ſo much conſiſt vpon titles and ritches, as in the diſcerninge &amp; iudging of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints and requeſts of his ſubiects &amp; in adminiſtri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Iuſtice vnto them. The prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce then of theſe <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</hi> &amp; <hi>Zela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</hi> is ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him a Warde, as that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely mark that they te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto, is to ſet him at his ful liberty again, which is to iudge lawfully (accordinge to the cuſtome of his Aunceſtours) vpon all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, &amp; complaints of his people: which libertie you haue cleane bereſt him of, &amp; yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſame vnto the Italian Pope, &amp; to the Prelats of the inquiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; barred him clene both from hearing &amp; iudging of his ſubiects cauſes. As touching the laſt point, wherin you ſay, <hi>That in your opinion his Maieſtye ought not to yelde vnto our requeſt, no not one iote:</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I do moſt of all marueile, that you woulde wiſh the K. to iudge no otherwyſe than as you liſt. If you be vaſſall to the K. leaue the choiſe to his Maieſtie, whether he wil yelde or not, and do not you preſcribe a law, before that he himſelf haue firſt herd our requeſts, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards giuen his iudgement vppon the ſame. Otherwiſe you will giue the worlde to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1223:60"/>how that you take the king to be ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, as that he cannot iudge of his owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, or els that your opinion muſt be a law, whereby his Maieſtie muſt of force be ruled. Well, if your opinion which you haue grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon your owne conceite, be ſo faſt ſettled in your ſtomacke as that you will not alter the ſame: Yet I woulde ye conſidered, that all the Eſtates and Cities in theſe quarters, be of an other minde. And peraduenture it may bee, that if the opinion of all the Eſtates in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral may be vnderſtood the greater part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilbe of our minde. If you thinck otherwyſe, why do yee not ſuffer the matter to come to proofe, by leauinge to his maieſtie full liberty to iudge &amp; diſcerne of all ſutes &amp; requeſts? except your meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g be, that we muſt of force take your opinion for the kings determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But ſurely for mine owne parte, I cannot yet be ſo well perſwaded of your great modeſtie &amp; wiſedome. Wherefore I am to requeſt you, that (without ſuffering your ſelfe to be any longer blinded wyth theſe cauilling pretences) you indeuour your ſelf in good faith &amp; true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, to further the tranquillity and quiet of theſe Countries, the which cannot by anye meanes be reeſtabliſhed, but by this, that the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1223:61"/>king may haue his auctoritie kept to himſelfe inuiolablie, in hearing and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes and controuerſies of all ſuch his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, as crye and call for his helpe and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye: that hee may ſee ſome remedie for the ſame, by the common aduice of the generall Eſtates of the Countrie, and that he ſuffer vs not to bee oppreſſed by the cruell tiranny of Strangers, who ſeeke nothing els but to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their couetous mindes and greedines of gaine, with the price of our bloude and wyth the vtter ouerthrow &amp; deſolacion of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in theſe Prouinces, to the great diminiſhing of his Maieſties Royall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, not caringe a point though all this go to wracke, ſo that they may returne into their Countries againe, loden &amp; charged with the ſpoile of vs, from the which I hope that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God will defende vs with his puiſſant Arme, as he hath done heretofore.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>IMPRINTED AT London in Fleetestreate by Thomas Marsh.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1576.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1223:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
